<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A perswasive to peace &amp; unity among Christians, notwithstanding their different apprehensions in lesser things</title>
            <author>Allen, William, d. 1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 191 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23668</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1068</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38421</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17466597</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17466597</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106454</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23668)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106454)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1625:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A perswasive to peace &amp; unity among Christians, notwithstanding their different apprehensions in lesser things</title>
                  <author>Allen, William, d. 1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 150 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for B. Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Allen by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian union.</term>
               <term>Concord --  Religious aspects.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106454:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106454:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PERSWASIVE TO Peace &amp; Unity AMONG CHRISTIANS, Notwithſtanding their different Apprehenſions in leſſer things.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 1.10.</hi>
               </bibl> Now I beſeech you, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, by the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that there be no Diviſions among you: but that ye be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly joyned together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame Judgment.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Phil. 2.2.</hi>
               </bibl> Fulfill ye my joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame Love, being of one accord, of one mind.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 14.19.</hi>
               </bibl> Let us therefore follow after the things which make for Peace, and things wherewith one may edifie another.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for B. <hi>Aylmer,</hi> at the Three Pigeons in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the <hi>Poultry.</hi> 1672.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:106454:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106454:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A PERSWASIVE TO Peace and Unity AMONG CHRISTIANS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE deep ſenſe of the very ill effects of our Church-Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions hath put me, as it ſhould do every good Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian, upon healing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. An account of ſome of which I ſhall give in the following Diſcourſe; which I ſhall ground on the words of St. <hi>Paul, Eph.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Endeavouring to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace.</hi> Which contain that behaviour, in part, by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106454:3"/>which Chriſtians may, and ought to walk worthy of that Vocation to which they are called: Unto which the Apoſtle doth, with the greateſt earneſtneſs, exhort and perſwade them, in this and the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Verſes. And the words give us oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to inquire into two things. 1. What is meant by the Unity of the Spirit. 2. How this Unity is preſerved by Peace, and how we are to endeavour ſo to preſerve it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is meant by the Unity of the Spirit? The Unity of the Spirit is that One-neſs among Chriſtians, which the Spirit of God worketh, or effecteth by the Goſpel, which is the Miniſtration of the Spirit. For by the Spirits operation through that, Men become one in Faith or Perſwaſion, one in Profeſſion, one in Affection, and one in Communion. And by their Union and agreement in theſe, or the three former of theſe, they become one Body or Spiritual Corporation under Chriſt the Head of it. <hi>By one Spirit we are all Baptized into one Body, and are made to drink into one Spirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.13.— <hi>For the work of the Miniſtry—till we all come to the Unity of the Faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God</hi> Epheſ. 4.12, 13.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are, by the Spirit, made one
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106454:3"/>in faith or perſwaſion touching the great fundamental truths in the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; ſuch as the Apoſtle doth inſtance in, in the three following Verſes: <hi>Even as ye were called in one hope of your Calling; One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, one God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all.</hi> Firſt, they are all called by the Goſpel to embrace Chriſtianity, in <hi>One Hope</hi> of obtaining forgiveneſs of ſins, and eternal Life. Secondly, they all agree in profeſſing Faith in <hi>One Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as the only Mediator, in oppoſition to the <hi>Lords many,</hi> the many Mediators the Heathen profeſſed to have, and to worſhip, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5, 6. Thirdly, they all agree in the Belief that the Doctrine of the Goſpel by Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, contained in the Holy Scriptures, is a revelation from God touching what Men ought to <hi>believe,</hi> and how they ought to <hi>live;</hi> called the <hi>[One Faith,]</hi> and <hi>the Common Faith,</hi> from the Chriſtians unanimous agreement in it, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.4. Fourthly, they all agree, and are one in the belief of <hi>One God and Father of all,</hi> in oppoſition to the many Idol-gods worſhipped by others. Fifthly, there is alſo <hi>One Baptiſm,</hi> by which all the Chriſtians, with one conſent, make
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106454:4"/>profeſſion ſolemnly of their belief in, and Dedication to the Worſhip and Service of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, into whoſe Name they were Baptized and by which, as by a ſacred Rite, they are ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly declared to be of the <hi>one Body,</hi> the Church. <hi>By one Spirit are all Baptized into one Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. They all agree, and are one, in the <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Common Faith,</hi> the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Doctrines of the Goſpel, the belief of which is of neceſſity to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Which Profeſſion is called <hi>The ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging of the truth which is after god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> Tit. 1.1. 2 Tim. 2.25. <hi>The acknowledgment of the Myſtery of God, and of the Father, and of Chriſt</hi> Col. 2.2. As with the heart they believe unto Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, ſo <hi>with the Mouth confeſſion is made unto Salvation,</hi> Rom. 10.10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. So far as they are Chriſtians indeed, they are all one in affection, or Brotherly Love. They Love all Men, even thoſe that are not Chriſtians, with a love of compaſſion, deſiring, and ſeeking their good; but they love their fellow Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians wiſh a ſpecial kind of love, for the appearance of good in them, for their one-neſs with them in the Faith, called, <hi>a loving, or the Truths ſake which is in them,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106454:4"/>2 John 1.2. And <hi>a loving them in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Tit. 3.15. By which they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>One <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Love.</hi> Act. 4.32. Col. 2.2. And hence it is that <hi>Faith in our Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, and love to all the Saints,</hi> are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently joyned together in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p n="4">4. All they that rightly be of the Unity of the Spirit, are alſo one in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. One in their Communion in <hi>Grace</hi> mutually loving one another, and praying one for another: One in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in <hi>Gifts,</hi> edifying one another as they have opportunity: And one in Communion in <hi>Ordinances;</hi> communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting together in Ordinances of Divine Worſhip, Spiritually with all, and locally with thoſe among whom they live; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17. <hi>For we being many are one Bread, and one Body; for we are all partakers of that one Bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the things in which the Unity of the Spirit doth eſpecially conſiſt. Not that I limit it to theſe only: for it is the work of the Spirit, in the Goſpel, to be bringing the Believers to <hi>ſpeak all the ſame thing, and to be perfectly joyned together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgment;</hi> in the leſſer things of Religion as well as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106454:5"/>the greater; but their actual agreement lyeth moſtly in the greater.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How this Unity is preſerved by Peace, and how we are to endeavour ſo to preſerve it.</p>
            <p>Unity in the whole community of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, &amp; is preſerved by each Member's obſerving the Laws and Rules made for the Government, and good Order of the whole in their carriage towards each other. For while every Man Acts his own part only, and keeps in his own Rank accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Rule, there is no confuſion, no diſturbance, no diviſion: and peace and confuſion, or diſorder, are put in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to one another, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33. Chriſt, the Head of the Church, or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Corporation, hath made ſeveral excellent Laws and Rules, to govern the Members of his Body in their behaviour one towards another, for the common good of the whole, and for the Honour of their Religion, and of him who is the great Founder of it. As that all their things ſhould be done in Charity: That they be gentle and courteous, humble and condeſcending, in Honour preferring one another: That they put on bowels of mercy and kindneſs: That they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear one another in love: That the ſtrong
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106454:5"/>bear the Infirmities of the weak: That they bear one anothers burthens: That they forgive one another: That they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh, exhort, and comfort one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as there is occaſion: That they have the ſame care one for another: That they provoke not one another: That they lay no ſtumbling block in one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers way: That all things be done to edifying: That they joyn together in ſolemn Acts of God's Worſhip as they have opportunity: That the Paſtours Teach and Rule the People well, and that the People learn of them, and obey them; and the like.</p>
            <p>Now, ſo far as theſe, and other like Laws are kept and obſerved, ſo far Peace and good Order is kept, and thereby Unity preſerved. For there is no rent or diviſion in the Body, till Men break the Laws of good Order. But ſo far as the Laws of good Order in the Chriſtian Community are broken, ſo far the peace thereof is diſturb'd; and to what degree the peace thereof is diſturb'd, to that degree is the Unity thereof weakned, and threatened to be broken, if it he not thereby broken indeed. As for inſtance; in caſe part of the Members of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity differ in their Opinions from the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106454:6"/>reſt, about undetermined circumſtances of Order or Worſhip; ſome holding theſe, and others holding thoſe beſt to agree with general Rules: If then either the one or the other do urge, or impoſe their own apprehenſions, or oppoſe the others that differ from them, to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent breach of the great Laws of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and general edification; Then is the Churches peace thereby diſturb'd, and the Unity thereof more or leſs broken; and then eminently ſo, when it proceeds to ſeparation.</p>
            <p>But when Chriſtians that agree in the eſſentials of Chriſtianity, do manage all their different apprehenſions about leſſer matters, eſpecially about undetermined circumſtances, and matters of doubtful diſputation, with ſuch Humility, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Meekneſs, Gentleneſs, Tenderneſs, Condeſcention and forbearance, as is no ways apt to diſcover in them any ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Brethren, or uncharitableneſs towards them, nor is any wayes apt to beget ſuch like diſtempers in their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren towards themſelves, to the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting of their mutual Communion; Then may they be truly ſaid to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace, though they otherwiſe differ in their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106454:6"/>thoughts about ſuch things: becauſe by ſuch a behaviour they obſerve the Laws of good Order, provided by our Lord and Maſter in ſuch caſes, as I ſhall ſhew more particularly afterwards.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, by what hath been thus ſaid in general, you may underſtand how we are to endeavour to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace; and that is, by a prudent and careful keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cloſe to the Laws which our Bleſſed Saviour hath given thoſe of his great Houſhold, to govern themſelves by, in their carriage one towards another, under all their different apprehenſions and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in ſuch like things as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And for the manner of endeavouring it; The phraſe and manner of ſpeaking, uſed in Scripture in preſſing this duty of Peace and Unity, plainly ſhews that the preſervation or recovery of it, is moſt induſtriouſly to be endeavoured. <hi>If it be poſſible, and as much as in you lyeth, live peaceably with all Men,</hi> Rom. 12.18. <hi>Seek peace, and enſue it,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.11. <hi>Follow Peace with all Men,</hi> Heb. 12.14. Though it flye from us, yet we muſt follow after it, and, if it be poſſible, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, and bring it back again. Nay, we are not only to follow after Peace, but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106454:7"/>alſo <hi>to follow after the things that make for peace,</hi> that tend to it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.19. And becauſe this is that which I principally deſign in theſe Papers, I ſhall enlarge my Diſcourſe the more about it. And what I ſhall ſay in ſhewing yet more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly how we are to endeavour to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace, may paſs under the name of Directions thereabout, if you pleaſe.</p>
            <div n="1" type="direction">
               <head>I. <hi>Direction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If we would endeavour it to purpoſe, we muſt lay the Foundation in the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Government of our own Spirits, in Humility and Charity, baniſhing thence ſuch paſſions and evil humours as will otherwiſe betray Men into unpeaceable practices, and make them diſturbers of the Churches Peace; and, conſequently, breakers of her Unity.</p>
               <p>A; firſt of all, we muſt lay aſide Pride, and Vain-glory, and manage all our mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters one with another, with lowlineſs of mind, meekneſs and modeſty. For un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian contention, which is contrary to Peace, ſprings from Pride and height of Spirit: <hi>Only by Pride cometh contention,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 13.10. By Pride
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106454:7"/>a Man over-values himſelf, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>values another: He over-values his own underſtanding, reaſoning, and judgment; and as much ſlights and undervalues anothers. This makes him impatient of oppoſition, and to think hardly of them that will not bow to his reaſonings, and judgment, and ſay as he ſays. The im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate deſire to maintain the epurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his own judgment, of which he hath ſo high a conceit, makes him over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look, or but ſlightly conſider what is offered by another in oppoſition to it, or differing from it. And hence ariſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate and unpeaceable contendings; eſpecially when the parties contending are both ſick of one Diſeaſe; though the one may have a better cauſe in hand then the other. This St. <hi>Paul</hi> cautioned the Chriſtians againſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.26. <hi>Let us not be deſirous of Vain-glory, provoking one another, envring one another.</hi> When Men are ambitious, and vain-glorious, would be thought ſome body, or to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear conſiderable in the account of others, every little oppoſition is apt to provoke their paſſion: and they in that paſſion are apt again to ſay and do that which tends to provoke others. And when the fire is by this means kindled, it is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106454:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>not eaſily quenched. For, <hi>Where envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſtrife is, there is confuſion, and every evil work,</hi> Jam. 3.16.</p>
               <p>But where Humility, Meekneſs, and Modeſty of mind bear ſway, there the Peace of the Church is in little danger of ſuffering by ſuch. Such will eſteem others better then themſelves, when they are ſcarce their equals: they will have a better opinion of their wiſdome and piety then of their own. And this diſpoſes them to <hi>look, not every Man on his own things, but alſo on the things of other;</hi> and as impartially, and with as much fairneſs to conſider and weigh what is offered by them, as what is offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by themſelves, and to be as willing, and ready to receive, as to give ſatisfaction. St. <hi>Paul</hi> well knew how conducible ſuch a tongue is to the peace and tranquillity of the Church, and to the comfort and benefit of Church-Communion, when he ſaid, <hi>Let nothing be done through ſtrife, or vain-glory, but in lowlineſs of mind let each eſteem other better than themſelves. Look not every man on his own things, but every man alſo on the things of others,</hi> Phil. 2.3, 4. And if, after all this fairneſs of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to give or to receive ſatisfaction, there yet remains a difference in judgment about
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106454:8"/>things which are not of the eſſence of Chriſtianity, yet there will be no unpeace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſtriving, nor contending, no ill and provoking reflexions among ſuch as are of this humble, and modeſt temper; but they will quietly, and patiently bear with one another in Love, as knowing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not to be infallible. <hi>The Servant of the Lord muſt not ſtrive, but be gentle unto all Men, patient, in meekneſs; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all meekneſs to all men;</hi> 2 Tim. 2.24, 25. Tit. 3.2. It was ſaid of our Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (who was meek, and lowly in heart) that <hi>he ſhall not ſtrive, nor cry, neither ſhall any man hear his voyce in the ſtreets;</hi> Mat. 12.19. And if this way of proceeding will not reconcile the different-minded to our judgment, when we have truth on our ſide, much leſs will any thing that we can do in a more imperious, and paſſionate way of proceeding. For <hi>the wrath of Man worketh not the Righteouſneſs of God:</hi> It is no fit Inſtrument or Tool for that Work, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.20. Whereas by a patient, and peaceable forbearance, not only Unity in affection and Communion is preſerved, but many times the diſsenting party won upon, and brought to a better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. <hi>By long forbearing is a Prince
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106454:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>perſwaded, and a ſoft Tongue breaketh the bone,</hi> Prov. 25.15.</p>
               <p>And as for Charity, there is nothing qualifies a Man more to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace then this. The ſeveral properties of it are deſcribed by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4-7 Do, as it were, conſpire, and naturally tend to promote peace and good agreement. To what degree Charity dwells in any Man, to that degree it diſpoſeth him to <hi>ſuffer long,</hi> and to forbear revenge; to be <hi>kind,</hi> and ready to do good: and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth him to <hi>Envy</hi> others in what they excell him; to <hi>vaunt himſelf,</hi> or to be <hi>puffed up;</hi> or to <hi>behave himſelf unſeemly,</hi> or unbecomingly in word or deed, or to <hi>ſeek his own,</hi> with neglect of others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit; or to be <hi>eaſily provoked:</hi> or to think or ſurmize <hi>evil,</hi> or to Interpret things to the worſt ſence, or to rejoyce in anothers halting, though an Adverſary: but inclines him to <hi>rejoyce in the Truth,</hi> and when right, to keep place: It enables a Man to <hi>bear with all things</hi> in another ſo far as is conſiſtent with his and the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral good: to believe all things that are any wayes credible, that tend to excuſe or commend others: To <hi>hope all things,</hi> and not to deſpair, but that a Neighbour may
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106454:9"/>by his Charitable endeavours be recovered, though he hath miſcarried: and to <hi>endure all things,</hi> labour, pains, and many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies to himſelf, ſo he may but be ſerviceable to others. And if theſe be the properties of Charity, well may it be called the bond of perfectneſs, and Chriſtians exhorted above all things to put it on. How can it be thought, that they can ever divide, or ſeparate, in whom Love with theſe properties dwells?</p>
               <p>And as Charity is of a healing, ſo it is alſo of a comprehenſive Nature: I can ſcarce propoſe any endeavours properly uſeful to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace, but more or leſs of theſe properties of Charity will be found in them. And it is ſo univerſally uſefull for the right conduct of all affairs in the Church, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives it in charge thus, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.14.) <hi>Let all your things be done with Charity:</hi> a line and vein of this ſhould run through all. And if all Chriſtians had but this <hi>ſalt in themſelves</hi> (to allude to <hi>Mark</hi> 9.) it would ſo ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon their converſe, that they would <hi>have peace one with another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where there is entireneſs of affection, and a peaceable correſpondence among Chriſtians, it makes them unwilling to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106454:10"/>differ from one another in judgment or practice. There is ſuch a <hi>comfort in Love</hi> (as the phraſe is, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1.) that it makes them very unwilling to admit of any difference that may diminiſh that comfort, or weaken that love. And this diſpoſeth them <hi>to look, not on their own things only, but alſo on the things of others,</hi> and to weigh, without prejudice or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allity, what each offers to other; which is the way to have the weaker brought over to the ſtronger, in any thing wherein they differ. And in this way doth the Church <hi>edifie it ſelf in love,</hi> Epheſ. 4.16. <hi>Being knit together in love, even unto all riches of full aſſurance of underſtanding,</hi> as the phraſe is, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.2. And indeed, it is a common thing for one Man to be brought over to anothers judgment through affection to him, being prepared thereby to give his reaſonings the greateſt liberty and ſcope in his judgment. Whereas, on the contrary, it is a ſtrong temptation to Men to differ from them in judgment and practice, from whom they have departed in affection. St. <hi>Paul</hi> could eaſily believe there were diviſions in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> when he fore-knew there would be Hereſies among them, the one being the fore-runner of the other,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106454:10"/>and a leſſer difference making way for a greater, as by ſad experience we have ſeen in our dayes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.18, 19. St. <hi>Paul</hi> obſerved it in ſome, who having firſt <hi>ſwerved from Charity, they quickly turned aſide unto vain jangling,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.5, 6. Whereas Love is the bond of perfectneſs, as it is called; it is the ſtrongeſt bond, it holds the parts longeſt, and faſteſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.14. It being a Maſter grace, and of a benigne Nature, it hath a kindly influence upon a mans judgment and whole practice. As <hi>the integrity of the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right doth guide them,</hi> ſo will their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity too. <hi>He that loveth his Brother abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the light, and there is no occaſion of ſtumbling in him,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.10. It is doubtleſs then more for want of love then want of light, when the Unity of the Spirit is not kept in the bond of peace.</p>
               <p>This then is the firſt Direction: that we would by a diligent uſe of all good means and motives, cheriſh and nouriſh Humility and Charity in our minds and Spirits, as principles of ſuch a peaceable behaviour, as directly tends to preſerve Unity in the Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="direction">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:106454:11"/>
               <head>II. <hi>Direction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This Unity is to be endeavoured to be kept in the bond of Peace by all good Chriſtians, by their being careful to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from <hi>deſpiſing and cenſuring</hi> one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon account of their different ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions about the leſſer things in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſo long as they are agreed in the main. Unleſs theſe be forborn in ſuch caſes, its next to an impoſſibility to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve peace and Unity among them. Theſe unchriſtian practices, as they are the effects of pride and uncharitableneſs, ſo they are, and have been two great peace-deſtroyers, and Church-dividers. There is, and ever hath been, and will be diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent meaſures of knowledge, underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and grace in the ſeveral Members of the ſame Body: Some are weak in the Faith, and ſome ſtrong; ſome Babes, and ſome ſtrong Men. Upon account of which difference of knowledge and grace, differences are apt more or leſs to ariſe among them. The weak are apt to be more ſcrupulous than the ſtrong, as being more in the dark, and ſo apter to ſtumble. Whereupon the ſtrong, if they be not reſtrained by Humility and Charity, are apt to deſpiſe them when they cannot
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106454:11"/>make them underſtand what is plain and evident to them themſelves. And the weak, again, if they be not reſtrained by Humility and Charity, are apt to judge and cenſure the ſtrong, as if they were not ſo conſcientious, becauſe not ſo ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous as themſelves. And upon this deſpiſing and judging one another, the bond of peace is broken, and a way pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for dividing. For when the weak ſee themſelves neglected, ſlighted, not regarded, and ſet at nought by the ſtrong, it diſcourages them, and takes off the pleaſure of their Society and Communion, and makes them weary of it, and becomes a temptation to them to forſake it, and to follow any oppoſite party that will head them. And when the ſtrong, again, find themſelves judged and cenſured by the weak, as if they were Men of little Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, they are apt to look upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as being, by ſuch prejudice taken up againſt them, put out of a capacity of ſerving them; which becomes a tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them to neglect them, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to eſtrange themſelves from them: Or, however, though that temptation ſhould not prevail ſo far upon them, yet all endeavours of the ſtrong to help and cure the weak, are by the prejudice which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106454:12"/>the weak have againſt them when they once fall to judging them, made very much ineffectual; ſo miſchievous and baneful to the Churches peace and Unity is proud deſpiſing, and uncharitable cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring one another.</p>
               <p>This was the caſe between the believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Jews and Gentiles, upon which the firſt conſiderable breach we read of brake out in the Chriſtian Church; of which we have an account in <hi>Act.</hi> 15. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. and other places. The believing Jews durſt not uſe ſuch liberty in meat as the believing Gentiles did: nor did the believing Gentiles think themſelves obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be circumciſed, and to obſerve Jewiſh Feſtivals, as the believing Jews thought they were. Hereupon the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Gentiles which underſtood their Liberty, deſpiſed the believing Jews when they could not make them underſtand it too. And the believing Jews, on the other hand, fell to judging the believing Gentiles as looſer than themſelves, and as Men of no Conſcience, becauſe they did not make Conſcience of Meats, and days of Circumciſion, as well as themſelves. And upon this unchriſtian carriage of one towards another under their different ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions in theſe things, great
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106454:12"/>diviſions, ſidings, and diſturbances among them, did enſue.</p>
               <p>Now, that all ſuch deſpiſing and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another, and dividing from one another about their difference in leſſer matters of doubtful diſputation, ſhould be forborn by Chriſtians, ſo long as they agree in the eſſentials of Chriſtianity, St. <hi>Paul</hi> declares, upon theſe two grounds, among others.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe upon the Common Faith wherein they were both agreed, they were at the firſt received by the Lord into his Church, and ſo into a near Relation to himſelf. And therefore their after-diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences which did not deſtroy that Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation upon which that Relation was firſt built, were no ſufficient ground of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing, or judging one another, or of dividing, or withdrawing one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This is plainly ſet down in theſe words: <hi>Let him that eateth not deſpiſe him that eateth not; and let not him which eateth not judge him that eateth, for God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him,</hi> Rom. 14.3. And this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is farther backed and urged again, Chap. 15.7. <hi>Wherefore receivere one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as Chriſt alſo received us to the glory of God.</hi> Thoſe whom God hath received into his Church upon ſuch and ſuch
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106454:13"/>grounds, we may not, we ought not to diſcourage, or reject, by deſpiſing, or judging, or withdrawing, ſo long as that remains in them upon which God at firſt received them. Which holds in all other caſes of difference between Chriſtians that agree in the main, as theſe did, as well as in this between the believing Jews and Gentiles. It is upon the like reaſon and ground that our Apoſtle, in the words upon which I found my diſcourſe, and thoſe following, (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.) preſſeth upon Chriſtians the great duty of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe they were at firſt incorporated into one Body by a profeſſion and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of one God and Father of all, of one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, of one Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Father and the Son, of one Doctrine of Faith, of one Hope, of one Baptiſm. Which fundamental points believed and lived to, are ſufficient to Salvation. And if ſo, they are ſufficient bonds of Union, and boundaries of Communion, whatever difference in leſſer things may otherwiſe occur. For more, in profeſſion, cannot be abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Church-Communion, then what in reality is abſolutely neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106454:13"/>For as the one doth conſtitute the Church as inviſible, ſo doth the other the Church as viſible. And the ſame thing which conſtitutes the Church as viſible, muſt needs inveſt the Members thereof in a right to its external priviledges. And if the Church had kept this her ground upon which ſhe was firſt built, and not made more conditions of Communion, ſhe had never been cut, mangled, and torn into (I know not how many) pieces, as ſhe hath been, and at this day is. And I ſee not any probability of her recovery to her primitive Union and Communion, till ſhe return to this her firſt Foundation of Union, and boundary of Communion. But a return to this would quickly do it, if all Chriſtians would acquieſce therein. And why they ſhould not as well as the primitive Chriſtians [the beſt Chriſtians that ever the World ſaw] did, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not, nor ever could hear any good reaſon to make me underſtand it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. St. <hi>Pauls</hi> other reaſon, why Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians that agree in the main, as aforeſaid, ſhould not deſpiſe, or judge, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from one another, for their differing in leſſer things, is this: becauſe both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties differing but only ſo, are to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, in the judgment of Charity, to aim
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106454:14"/>at the pleaſing of God in what they diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently hold and do. For Charity, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which we are to guide our ſelves in all ſuch caſes of difference, <hi>think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no evil,</hi> but <hi>believeth,</hi> and <hi>hopeth all things</hi> concerning others, in the beſt ſence and conſtruction their Actions are capable of. This was the caſe of the believing Jews and Gentiles; they both aimed at the pleaſing of God even in thoſe things wherein they differed. <hi>He that regardeeh the day, regardeth it to the Lord; and he that regardeth not the day, to the Lord he doth not regard it. He that eateth eateth to the Lord,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for he giveth God thanks; and he that eateth not, to the Lord he eateth not, and giveth God thanks,</hi> Rom. 14.6. Both aimed at the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving themſelves to God in their contrary wayes. And if the Lord in ſuch a caſe will not deſpiſe, or judge ſuch an one, ſo as to condemn him, though under a miſtake but of that Nature, as certainly he will not, but pity and pardon him, (for <hi>he hath compaſſion on them that are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and out of the way</hi>) much leſs ſhould we, who are fallible our felves, and <hi>compaſſed about with infirmities. Who art thou that judgeſt another mans Servant?</hi> (ſaith our Apoſtle) <hi>to his own Maſter he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106454:14"/>ſtandeth or falleth: every one of us ſhall give an account of himſelf to God:</hi> Let <hi>us not therefore judge one another any more,</hi> ver. 4.12, 13. for that is a judgment belongs not unto us. <hi>There is one Law-giver, and one Judge;</hi> who art thou that judgeſt another? <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.12. That is, what doſt thou make thy ſelf to be, that dareſt to undertake ſuch a thing?</p>
               <p>And as we ſhould be afraid to judge one another, ſo we ſhould of deſpiſing one another in any caſe like that before mentioned; for our Saviours ſerious ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veat againſt it, argues it to be both much againſt his mind, and of dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to our ſelves and others: <hi>Take heed that ye deſpiſe not one of theſe little Ones,</hi> Mat. 18.10. He knew that his little Ones, becauſe but little Ones in knowledge and grace, that have little of theſe to render their fellowſhip much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable, are apt to be neglected and ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to be thereby diſcouraged, and turned aſide: he therefore cautions thoſe that are ſtronger, to take heed leſt they ſhould be betrayed into any carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them as ſignifies their ſlighting of them. Our Saviour had ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, how ſad a thing it would be for any Man to be inſtrumental in turning any
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106454:15"/>weak Chriſtian aſide by any undue car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage towards him, when he ſaid, in ver. 6. <hi>Wo be to the World becauſe of offences,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and wo be to him by whom the offence cometh.</hi> And it would be far more Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like (of whom it is ſaid, <hi>He ſhall not break the bruiſed Reed, nor quench the ſmoaking Flax</hi>) to uſe more care, pains, and tenderneſs towards the weak and feeble, to preſerve and increaſe that little ſpark of Chriſtianity in them, though it be no more, and though there be no more appearance of it, than there is of fire when only ſmoak can be diſcerned, then towards thoſe that are ſtrong, and do not ſtand in ſo very much need of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs in our carriage, and applications to them. Which alſo agrees excellently well with St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Metaphorical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.23, 24, 25. <hi>Thoſe Members of the Body, which we think to be leſs honourable, upon theſe we beſtow more abundant honour, and our uncomely parts have more abundant comelineſs. For our comely parts have no need: but God hath tempered the Body together, having given more abundant honour to that part which lacked, that there ſhould be no Schiſm in the Body:</hi> implying, that certainly there will be, where ſuch care, &amp; tenderneſs of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106454:15"/>is not uſed towards ſuch as are leaſt accounted of in the Church. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lift up the hands which hang down, and the feeble knees, and make ſtraight paths for your feet</hi> (by removing all diſcouraging impediments out of the way) <hi>leſt that which is lame be turned out of the way, but rather let it be healed: looking diligently, leſt any fail of the grace of God,</hi> Heb. 12.12, 13, 15. How far all parties of Men among us have made themſelves guilty of breaking the Peace and Unity of the Church, by this unchriſtian deſpiſing, and judging one another, concerns them to conſider; and the guilty to repent of what is paſt, and to reform for time to come, that they may not be judged and condemned by God for what they have done. That's the ſecond Direction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="direction">
               <head>III. <hi>Direction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Thoſe that would keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace, muſt be careful to forbear all hard ſpeeches, and ill reflexions on them that differ from them; eſpecially tale-bearing, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting, and whiſpering. They muſt make no ill repreſentation of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther behind their backs, by raking up,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106454:16"/>and then ſcattering abroad all the evil they can, or whatever may tend to the diſparagement, or reproach of ſuch as differ from them. Becauſe, if they ſhould be guilty herein, though they may think thereby to weaken the Reputation of the Cauſe they oppoſe, yet in truth they will be ſo far from reconciling their Opponent to <hi>their</hi> Cauſe, as that they will thereby diſhonour it, and render it the more ſuſpected; and Communion with themſelves ſo much the leſs deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and all their own arguings the leſs available, and by-ſtanders the readier to fall in with thoſe of a better behaviour, as judging thereby their Cauſe to be better, though in it ſelf it ſhould be worſe: for a good Cauſe may be ſpoiled in the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. All ſuch unchriſtian carriage tends to exaſperate, imbitter, and provoke the Spirits of their Opponents, both againſt them and their Cauſe, and to widen the breach more and more, and to ſet them at the greater diſtance, and to make them the more irreconcilable. <hi>A froward Man ſoweth ſtrife</hi> (ſaith the Wiſe man) <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.28. <hi>Grievous words ſtir up anger, and the forcing of wrath bringeth forth ſtrife: and the words of a tale-bearer are as wounds,</hi> Prov. 15.1. and 26.22. and 30.33. So
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106454:16"/>true it is that <hi>the wrath of man doth not work the Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> Jam. 1.20. It is not for the intereſt of the Truth, nor doth it any wayes advantage the cauſe of God. No, if any Man would ſee any good effect of his endeavours towards the Uniting of Men, if he would ſee the Seed he ſows come up; let him be ſure to avoid all harſh and unpeaceable proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings therein. <hi>The Fruit of Righteouſneſs is ſown in Peace of them that make Peace,</hi> Jam. 3.18. <hi>The Servant of God muſt not ſtrive, but be gentle to all,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.24. As we muſt follow Peace with all Men, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. So, in order thereto, we muſt <hi>ſpeak evil of no Man,</hi> Tit. 3.2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="direction">
               <head>IV. <hi>Direction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In Order to our keeping the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace, we muſt ſtudy rather to agree with, than to differ from one another: and be more ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to find out what will bring us nearer together, than what will ſet us at a greater diſtance. And this is one way of <hi>follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the things which make for peace;</hi> and of <hi>ſtudying to be quiet;</hi> to both which we are exhorted, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.20. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.11. And to this end, I ſhall recommend theſe three things.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:106454:17"/>
               <p n="1">1. To make Conſcience of endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as truly and ſincerely to find out what may make us of their mind that differ from us, if it be to be found out, as what may tend to make them of our mind. We ſhould be as much afraid of offending againſt the publick Peace, and Charity of the Church, as againſt Truth; of being guilty of Schiſm in practice, as of error in judgment; and take as much pains to keep our ſelves from a cauſleſs differing from others, as to make them agree with us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That we do as impartially weigh what thoſe that differ from us do offer for our ſatisfaction, as what we our ſelves do offer to ſatisfie them. In doing of which we ſhall in part diſcharge that duty enjoyned us, in <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.4. Look not every Man on his own things, but every Man alſo on the things of others. And by this we ſhall make it appear, that we are willing to agree with thoſe that differ from us, as far as poſſibly we can, as far as any reaſon or ground appears to bear us out in ſo doing. And if we herein begin to thoſe which differ from us, it will induce them, if there be any candor in them, to return the like to us. And this is the way to reduce the difference to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106454:17"/>a narrow compaſs, and to make it as little as may be. And when it appears to be but little, it will be the eaſier to ſatisfie one another about it: or, however, we ſhall then be the better able peaceably to bear with one another in it. But if this be not done, it will beget a ſuſpition that we affect to differ, and to ſtrive for Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry more than for Truth and Peace; and that it is more from a ſpirit of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction than Conſcience, that we differ.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When any alter their judgment ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon grounds found out by their own ſearch and ſtudies, or offered to them by others, ſo that they come over to them in whole, or in part, from whom they differed before, then beware of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting this as matter of <hi>Odium</hi> and reproach to them, ſo long as they are not worſe in their Morals. The contrary, that is, the doing ſo, hath been an ill practice, and ſuch as hath tended greatly to block up the way of a due, and Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian compliance with them from whom, through miſtake, they have once pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly differed. While it hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented as matter of reproach to Men, not to ſtand their ground, and to be true to their principles they have once receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though found erroneous enough
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106454:18"/>when better conſidered and looked into, it hath proved a great temptation doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs unto many, to neglect an impartial and thorow-examination of the grounds of their Opinion or practice, and to be prejudiced againſt all that is offered by others to convince them of miſtake. Mens Reputation among their party is a dangerous ſnare to hold them faſt in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and a great impediment to their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and diſcerning the Truth when it is declared to them, when it tends to draw them off, and to expoſe them to reproach among their party, and a great prejudice and bar againſt their receiving and owning of it. <hi>Why do ye not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand my ſpeech? Even becauſe ye cannot hear my word,</hi> ſaid our Saviour to the Jews, <hi>John</hi> 8.43. They had no mind to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace his Doctrine, which would bring them into diſgrace with their party, the Phariſees, and therefore they had no mind ſo to conſider it, as to underſtand it. Which made our Saviour ſay again, <hi>How can ye believe which receive honour one of another, and ſeek not the honour that cometh from God only?</hi> Joh. 5.44. But if Men would but underſtand, and conſider that it is truly honourable, and praiſe-worthy in the ſight of God, and Wiſe Men, to love
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106454:18"/>and own Truth where ever they find it, and however diſguiſed by its Adverſaries, and to be of open and free minds to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, and try all things, and when they diſcover Truth, to buy it at any rate, though it coſt them more than the loſs of their Reputation among an erring party; they would then neither fright others, nor be ſcared themſelves from exchanging error for Truth, Schiſm for Peace and Unity, by reproachful nick-names.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="direction">
               <head>V. <hi>Direction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Thoſe that would keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace, had need to be of publick Spirits, and ſtill to ſeek their own perſonal and private ſatisfaction in ſubordination to a publick good, and not in oppoſition to it: to preſerve the publick Peace and Unity of the Church, and the benefits that depend thereon, before the pleaſing of themſelves in things not abſolutely neceſſary, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient only. If this be not obſerved, there will be no avoiding diviſions and ſeparations. And the Reaſon hereof is taken from the different apprehenſions, capacities, and tempers of the ſeveral parts and Members of the Church. By
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106454:19"/>reaſon of this, thoſe circumſtances about the adminiſtration of Holy things, which will beſt pleaſe ſome good Men, will not ſo well ſatisfie others. This we find to be true by the different uſages of the parts of the Reformed Church in ſeveral Nations, and by the different perſwaſions and inclinations of the parts of the Church in one and the ſame Nation, yea, in one and the ſame City, Town, and Pariſh, as is well known. So that, if one part of the Church ſhould refuſe Communion with the other in the ſame Ordinances, unleſs they can have them adminiſtred upon terms beſt pleaſing to themſelves; and if the other part of the Church, of a different opinion therein, ſhould do ſo too; ſeparation follows of courſe, till they can all be of one mind in thoſe diſputable things.</p>
               <p>But in all ſuch caſes the publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of Religion ſhould ſway more with us, than what otherwiſe would be more to our liking. The profit of the whole is more to be attended, than the pleaſing of our ſelves, when the queſtion is not, which is good, and which is ſimply bad, this or that? But only, which is better, this or that? St. <hi>Paul</hi> walked by this Rule, in bearing with, yea, in chuſing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106454:19"/>ſome things for publick edification ſake, when circumſtances made them neceſſary thereunto, which out of thoſe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he would not have choſen, nor could well bear with. <hi>Even as I</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>pleaſe all Men in all things, not ſeeking my own profit, but the profit of many, that they may be ſaved,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.33. Under ſome circumſtances he would forbear things, which under others he would not: and thus he would <hi>eat no meat while the World ſtands, rather than make his Brother to offend.</hi> He choſe to labour with his own hands for his ſupport, rather than to take Money from others when he ſaw the intereſt of the Chriſtian Religion would be diſadvantaged thereby. And he Circumciſed <hi>Timothy,</hi> purified himſelf, and took on him a Vow, after the Jewiſh mode, when ſo to do tended to publick good, though otherwiſe the doing of ſuch things could not be without ſome regret to him, conſidering how ſlightingly he ſpeaks of them at other turns. And thus he took up and laid down many things, even as the publick intereſt of Religion lead him to it. To them that were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, he became as one under the Law; and as without <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law to them that were without it: and all this
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106454:20"/>he reckoned to be conſiſtent with his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>under the Law to Chriſt.</hi> To the weak he became as weak, that he might gain the weak: he was made all things to all men, but it was <hi>for the Goſpels ſake,</hi> as he ſaith; and that he might by all means ſave ſome: it was, that he might gain the freer paſſage and readier reception of the goſpel, for the Salvation of men, 1 Cor. 9.2.23. And accordingly he exhorted others to walk by the ſame rule, and to conſider, and do, what would beſt conſiſt with publick benefit, rather then what would beſt pleaſe and gratifie themſelves. <hi>We that are ſtrong ought to bear the infirmities of the weak, and not to pleaſe our ſelves,</hi> Rom. 15.1. Look not every man on his own things, but every man alſo on the things of others, <hi>Phil</hi> 2.4.</p>
               <p>If Chriſtians on all hands among us had but acted and walked according to this rule; nay, if the diſſenters would but have done it when the other could not be prevailed with; the publick intereſt of Religion would not have been expoſed to that loſs and dammage as it is at this day. And therefore, as that publick benefit which might have been procured, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by ſuch yielding and condeſcending as circumſtances made not only Lawful,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106454:20"/>but neceſſary, might have been a forcible motive ſo to have done: ſo the publick dammage and miſchief which a non-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance under our circumſtances tends to, may, and ought alſo to be a powerful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive from maintaining, and continuing our diſtance upon ſuch ſlight grounds as thoſe are which have brought us to it. For ſuch a diſtance tends to keep open a wide breach in the Body of the Nation, to the weakening of it, and rendering it obnoxious to the Envy, ill will, or am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of any publick Adverſary; or to create one if there were none: it tends to the diſhonour and reproach of the Nation: it tends to weaken the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant intereſt, and to bring a ſcandal and reproach upon our Religion it ſelf, and to put an Advantage into the hands of the Adverſaries of it: it tends to lay a ſtumbling-block in the way of ſuch as are Atheiſtically inclined: it tends to diſtract, and unſettle the Peoples minds about the more neceſſary points of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; or, at leaſt, to divert them from the ſerious practice of them: and it tends to the diſtraction of Chriſtian Charity. And that which tends to any one of theſe, tends to a publick hurt and dammage; how much more that which tends to them all?
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106454:21"/>And in good ſadneſs, are the things on either hand about which we differ, of ſuch neceſſity or value, as that for the ſake thereof the publick intereſt of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and of the Nation, ſhould run ſuch hazards, and ſuſtain ſuch apparent dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage by contending for them as they do? Or, can it be thought, when ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that God, who hath ſaid, <hi>I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired Mercy, and not Sacrifice; and the knowledge of God rather than burnt-offerings</hi> (which yet were his own inſtitutions) is ſuch a lover of thoſe things which are but circumſtances of inſtitutions at moſt, wherein our difference as to communion of private Members lies, as that he had rather the intereſt of Religion in the main, and of National Societies of Men ſhould deeply ſuffer, then that thoſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances ſhould be either waved, or born withall? Me-thinks, thoſe who have not Love and Zeal enough for Religion to be reſtrained from ſuch dividing wayes and practices as evidently tend to its great prejudice, ſhould yet be reſtrained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from upon account of their own ſecular intereſt, as that is expoſed thereby to great hazards, as that is involved in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Fate of the Nation; alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring who hath ſaid, <hi>A Nation
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106454:21"/>divided againſt it ſelf, is brought to deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="direction">
               <head>VI. <hi>Direction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Thoſe that would keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace, had need to be careful not to impoſe upon their Chriſtian Brethren, as conditions of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, things of doubtful diſputation, or which are not ſome way neceſſary to further the great ends of Religion. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, though ſome ſuch things may not be unlawful in themſelves, yet ſo long as they are thought to be ſo by many, it will occaſion a breach, as experience ſhews that from time to time it hath done. And when the impoſition of any thing that is apt to do ſo, may be forborn without any detriment to Chriſtianity in its end or means, without any diſhonour to God, or wrong to Mens Souls; it ſeems altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther incongruous, then to impoſe it. When the believing Gentiles would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon the believing Jews to uſe the ſame Liberty in Meat which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves did, when thoſe Jews were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded it was unlawful for them ſo to do: and when, again, the believing Jews would impoſe upon the believing Gentiles
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106454:22"/>the obſervation of dayes, and other le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Rites which the Gentiles ſcrupled, and that they fell to judging one another hereupon; St. <hi>Paul</hi> interpoſed, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, and perſwaded them, that inſtead of this, they would judge this rather, as better becoming them, that <hi>no man put a ſtumbling-block, or an occaſion to fall in his Brothers way:</hi> that they would not by impoſitions, tempt one another to do that which they could not do with ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Conſcience, or elſe to ſeparate: And to put one another upon a neceſſity of doing either the one or the other, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued great uncharitableneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.13. And when he had, in ver. 1. exhorted the ſtrong to receive the weak into their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, he cautions them, that by no means they would trouble them with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of doubtful diſputation.</p>
               <p>That agreement of Chriſtians in the ſubſtance of Doctrine and Worſhip, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they became one Body at the firſt, is doubtleſs ſufficient, without any addition, to continue that Union in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. And upon this very thing was the Communion of the Apoſtolical Churches Founded: And the going off from this, and the adding ſuch conditions of Communion as are not found in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106454:22"/>Scripture, hath been Fatal to the Churches Peace, and that which hath, from time to time, broken it into pieces. Men ſhould alwayes make choice of means fitted to their end. And therefore thoſe who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign the eſtabliſhing of Peace and Unity in the Church, ſhould beware of impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſuch things on their Brethren as are like to prove a bone of contention, when they may be forborn without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to any. The contrary many times proves (as I have ſaid) very miſchievous to the Church. As Parents tempt their Children to withdraw that reverence and obedience which is due in things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by impoſing upon them unneceſſarily, out of humour, (againſt which they are cautioned, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.) So Mens greater Extravagancies in the Church, frequently take their firſt riſe from the impoſing of ſuch things on them which might well have been forborn.</p>
               <p>In the choice of Circumſtances about Worſhip wherein there is a liberty of choice, it would alwayes, for Peace and Unity ſake, be conſidered, what the People are able to bear: a thing which our firſt Reformers had an eye to; and <hi>Moſes</hi> would never have permitted di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce, but that the temper of the people
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106454:23"/>lead him to it: <hi>He ſuffered it for the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their hearts.</hi> Our Saviour alſo in his conduct had reſpect to the capacity and temper of the People; he preached to them <hi>as they were able to bear,</hi> Mar. 4.33. And did forbear to declare many things to his Diſciples which he had to ſay, <hi>Becauſe they could not hear them then,</hi> John 16.12.</p>
               <p>Chriſtians of all Capacities, whether their ſtanding be higher or lower in the Church, are to do nothing to one another, but what doth well conſiſt with Love. The precept is Univerſal both in reſpect of Perſons and things: <hi>Let all your things be done with Charity,</hi> 1. Cor. 16.14. <hi>By Love ſerve one another,</hi> Gal. 5.13. <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing one another in Love,</hi> Epheſ. 4.2. The very ſeverities of Excommunication are to proceed from Love to the delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents ſoul; <hi>That the Spirit may be ſaved in the day of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nothing ſhould be impoſed that ſavours of want of Love or tenderneſs; No burdening of one anothers Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, but rather <hi>bearing one anothers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, and ſo fulfilling the Law of Chriſt:</hi> Imitating St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>I was gentle among you, even as a Nurſe cheriſheth her Children.</hi> And without doubt, this
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106454:23"/>is the beſt method to preſerve and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe Peace, Love, and Unity, and the edification of the Church; <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.16. Edifying it ſelf in Love.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="direction">
               <head>VII. <hi>Direction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Thoſe that would endeavour to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace, as they ought, muſt not ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on any ſide for external circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces about the adminiſtration of holy things, as thereby to expoſe the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantials of Chriſtianity, Peace, Charity, and Unity, to ruine and deſtruction. For the preſervation of that which is moſt eſſential to the keeping of the Unity of the Spirit, as Peace and Charity are, is more to be endeavoured, than the retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what is but circumſtantial to it, as a more or leſs convenient mode of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration is. The Unity of the Spirit may be kept in the uſe of a leſs convenient mode of Adminiſtration, when a more convenient cannot be had without the loſs of Peace, Charity, and Unity: but the Unity of the Spirit cannot be kept where Peace and Charity are ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
               <p>Peace, Charity, and Unity, are duties
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106454:24"/>of a higher Nature than circumſtances about Adminiſtrations that are not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary, but only more conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. To love our Neighbour as our ſelves, is <hi>the Royal Law,</hi> (Jam. 2.10.) one of the two great Commandments, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 22.39.) <hi>the fulfilling of the Law,</hi> (Rom. 13.10.) <hi>the more excellent way,</hi> (1 Cor. 12.31.) greater than Faith or Hope, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. laſt ver. And ſo, Peace is that in which, together with Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt, the Kingdome of God conſiſts, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17.) and which is to <hi>Rule</hi> in our hearts, and to over-rule in many caſes, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.15. Charity and Peace are great Moral duties, in which much of the Chriſtian Religion, in the power of it, doth conſiſt, as being that wherein a Man moſt reſembles God, and by which God dwells in him, and he in God, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.16. And when theſe fall into competition with circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances relating not to the being, but only to the better conſtitution of Churches and Miniſtry, and the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Ordinances in a better mode, and to the better exerciſe of diſcipline and government; they are to give place to Peace, Love, and Unity; and not Peace, Love, and Unity, to them.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:106454:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe thoſe are but means ſubordinate and ſubſervient to theſe as their end: and the means, as ſuch, are no farther uſeful than they are ſerviceable to their end. Which may be the reaſon why waſhing of Saints feet, the gifts of Charity, the annointing the Sick with Oyl in the Name of the Lord, have been diſ-uſed, though otherwiſe once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe controverted points about the betterneſs of wayes and modes of Adminiſtration, on which ſide ſoever the Truth falls, are not things wherein the glory of God, the Honour and ſucceſs of Religion, and the good and Salvation of Men are ſo much concerned, as they are in the great duties of Love, Peace, and Unity, and what depends upon theſe: and therefore it muſt needs be a duty of a higher Nature, and of greater obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſecure and promote Love, Peace, and Unity, which are the greater, than the betterneſs of Modes of Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which are but the leſs. And a Man's duty in the leſs is to be pleaded only in ſubordination to his duty in the greater, but never in oppoſition to it. And therefore well might. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, <hi>[above all theſe things] put on Charity,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106454:25"/>which is the bond of perfectneſs,</hi> Col. 3.14. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> likewiſe: <hi>[above all things] have fervent Charity among your ſelves.</hi> 1 Pet. 4.12. And if above all things, then above the circumſtances relating to the conſtitution of Churches, to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, Adminiſtration of Holy things, and diſcipline. I might both amplifie, and exemplifie this, and over-prove it, in ſhewing how that duties which become ſo only by inſtitution, are alwayes to give way to Moral duties, when they come in competition. <hi>I will have Mercy, and not Sacrifice,</hi> Hoſ. 6.6. Mat. 9.13. and 12.7. <hi>Go, and be firſt reconciled to thy Brother, and then come and offer thy gift;</hi> Mat. 5.24. Circumciſion waited upon, and was ſuſpended, upon a Moral neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, forty years in the Wilderneſs, being intermitted ſo long, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 5. Now then, if poſitive precepts themſelves are ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeded by Moral, when they come into competition; then ſo are thoſe things much more which are but circumſtances relating to inſtitutions, and ſuch circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances too, as that it is matter of diſpute among Wiſe and good Men on both ſides, which, whether theſe or thoſe, do beſt agree with the Nature and ends of thoſe inſtitutions.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:106454:25"/>
               <p>Now, that our dividing, ſeparating, and running into parties, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the leſſer things fore-mentioned, does tend to the decay and deſtruction of Love, as well as Peace and Unity, is a thing too apparent in our own experience, to need proof. That which is an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſeparation, will certainly leſſen, if it do not quite deſtroy Love. The Law of Commandments contained in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, which was a Wall of Separation, or partition, between Jews and Gentiles, is called the <hi>Enmity,</hi> Epheſ. 2.15. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, as it did ſeparate them, it was the cauſe of enmity, and laid waſte Charity, as all ſeparation upon a Religious account ever hath done, more or leſs. And to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny this, whatever one of late hath ſaid to the contrary, is to contradict the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſenſe and experience of Men. And therefore what is our dividing upon the terms before deſcribed, but a Method of ſeeking to purchaſe little things in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the loſs of great? Of ſecuring Circumſtances, with the loſs of ſubſtance; of obtaining ſuppoſed conveniencies, with the loſs of what is certainly, and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary: it is as if they ſhould have Robbed the Temple to build a Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue. And I fear this will be found an
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106454:26"/>ill way of trading with our Maſter's Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, and ſuch as will turn but to a bad account, when profit and loſs is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted. The want of a due care to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Charity before things leſs conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, hath betrayed many a one into that which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls vain jangling, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5, 6. <hi>The end of the Commandment</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is Charity, from which ſome having ſwerved</hi> (or not aiming at, as it is in the Margin,) <hi>have turned aſide to vain jangling.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="direction">
               <head>VIII. <hi>Direction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>To the keeping of the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace, its greatly neceſſary to take heed of dividing Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Becauſe theſe eſpecially are the ſpring of irregular motion, of breaking aſunder inſtead of Uniting. There are indeed other cauſes of unlawful diviſions and ſeparations; but they ſcarce ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to any height in producing ſuch effects, without this. Pride, Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitedneſs, Uncharitableneſs, and affection of ſingularity, are alſo cauſes of this evil: but theſe uſually Act under the colour of ſome one or more miſtaken Principles. I ſhall inſtance in ſome of them, and inſiſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106454:26"/>the longer upon them, becauſe they are the Weapons in which Church-Dividers do uſually put their truſt. Some of them relate to the qualification of Church-Members, and the conſtitution of Churches: ſome to the Worſhip per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in Churches; and ſome to the Magiſtrates Authority enjoyning that Worſhip. I ſhall begin with what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the qualification of Perſons of which Churches are conſtituted.</p>
               <div n="1" type="dividing_principle">
                  <head>I. <hi>Dividing Principle to be avoided.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>That Churches Founded in Infant-Baptiſm, are not to be held Communion with.</p>
                  <p>This tenet is built upon a ſuppoſition that Baptiſm adminiſtred to Infants is a <hi>Nullity,</hi> is invalid, and no Baptiſm, and that therefore Churches made up of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dobaptiſts, are no true Churches. To this I have two things to ſay. 1. That they of this way, will never be able to prove Infant-Baptiſm a Nullity. 2. That if they could prove it an errour, yet they cannot prove it to be an errour of that Nature, as will be a ſufficient ground of ſeparation.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, they will never be able to prove
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106454:27"/>it a Nullity, and till they do prove it to be ſo, they will never be able to juſtifie ſeparation upon account of it. For if they pronounce them no true Churches, and renounce Communion with them upon that account, they muſt prove their charge, or lye under the blame of a falſe accuſation, and an unjuſt ſeparation. It lyes on their part to prove their refuſing Church-communion with ſuch, to have a ſufficient ground to juſtifie their practice. If ever they prove Baptiſm adminiſtred to the Infants of Believers to be a Nullity, it muſt be, 1. By diſproving their Church-Relation. And, 2. By proving their excluſion out of Chriſt's Commiſſion to Baptize; and thirdly, by proving that the ends of Baptiſm are not attained, when adminiſtred to them. And that they are never like to do this, conſider what I have to offer to make you think ſo.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That they cannot diſprove ſuch to be of the Church, if they ſhould atempt it, I have two things to lay in their way.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that the ſame Jewiſh Children which were viſibly of the Church immediately before their Parents became Chriſtians at the firſt,
<note place="margin">☞</note>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:106454:27"/>continued to be ſo after. The reaſon of which affection is this; Becauſe they were not under the diſchurching cauſe of as many of the Jews as were diſchurched, and that was unbelief, and wilful diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in rejecting the Goſpel; of which they could not be guilty by any Act of their own, or of their Parents, as impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them. <hi>Becauſe of unbelief,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, they were broken off,</hi> Rom. 11.20. See alſo <hi>John</hi> 8.35. If it be ſaid they were diſchurched in the diſſolution of the Jewiſh Church-ſtate in general; it is but an evaſion which will not help them: for the fore-cited Text is flatly againſt them. For all that were not broken off by unbelief, did continue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broken off; that is, they ſtill kept their place and ſtanding in the Church of God. And therefore to aſſign any other cauſe of diſchurching any than the Scripture hath aſſigned; or, at leaſt, any other without this here aſſigned and determined by the Apoſtle, is too great preſumption, and ſuch as will not ſatisfie an impartial mind.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, our Saviour hath declared, little Children to be of the Church, when he ſaid, <hi>of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> Mat. 19.14. If any by Kingdome of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106454:28"/>Heaven have a mind to underſtand it of the Kingdom of Glory, yet they may remember, that none are of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Glory, who were not firſt of the Church, firſt of the Kingdome of Grace here. So that it comes all to one, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it of which you will.</p>
                  <p>If they ſhall ſay, that by <hi>Such,</hi> here is not meant ſuch in age, but ſuch in quality, ſuch as are like Children in Humility and Innocency: The ſcope of the place, and the purpoſe to which the words are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, will not ſuffer them ſo to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them. For the words, of ſuch is the Kingdome of Heaven, are our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's reaſon by which he would take off his Diſciples from hindering little Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, properly taken, from being brought unto him, and of juſtifying their practice that brought them. <hi>Suffer little Children to come unto me, and forbid them not,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for of ſuch is the Kingdome of Heaven.</hi> And if we ſhould underſtand by ſuch, not ſuch Children properly, but Men, like ſuch in quality, we deſtroy the force and ſence of our Saviour's reaſon, and render it wholly inconſequent. For it doth not follow at all that becauſe the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven is of other Perſons like little Children in ſome other things, but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:106454:28"/>altogether unlike them in what was the matter of exception againſt their being brought to Chriſt, which was their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority or infancy, that therefore little Children properly underſtood, ought to be ſuffered, and not forbidden to be brought to Chriſt. Such a rendring the ſence would faſten a fallacy of four terms on our Saviour's words, of putting one thing in the premiſes, and another in the concluſion, as you will ſee if you caſt them into a ſyllogiſm.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, our Saviour plainly declared the Relation of little Children to himſelf, when, at another time, he taking a little Child, ſaid, <hi>Whoſoever receiveth</hi> [this] <hi>little. Child in my Name, receiveth me.</hi> Luk. 9.48. For how could a little Child be received in his Name, if it were not viſibly related to him? To receive one in Chriſt's Name, and to receive one becauſe he belongs to Chriſt, is one and the ſame thing, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.41.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If ſuch Children then are of the Church, and Related to Chriſt; to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize them, cannot be proved unlawful. And the reaſon is, becauſe the ſame thing which qualifies any Perſons for Church-Member-ſhip, qualifies them for Baptiſm. And Baptiſm is a ſacred Rite of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106454:29"/>inſtituted by Chriſt, ſolemnly to publiſh and declare ſuch to be of the Church as are Baptized: it is a Chriſtian badge to declare to whom they do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long. There is one Body, and one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm for all of that one Body, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.4, 5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If the Infants of believing Parents be of the Church, it cannot be proved that they are excluded out of Chriſt's Commiſſion to be Baptized, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18. And the reaſon is plain, becauſe they can never be diſproved to be Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt in one ſence or other, that are viſibly of the Church. For the Church is Chriſt's School: and all that are of the Church, are Chriſt's Scholars. If they ſay, Infants are no Diſciples, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not in a capacity to learn; I anſwer. Although they are not in the propereſt, and neareſt capacity to learn, yet it doth not therefore follow, that they are in no ſuch capacity of it, as that they may be called, and reputed to be Diſciples, or Learners. The Scripture uſeth to reckon, or impute the doing of things to Children, when yet they have been but in as remote a capacity of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe things themſelves, as they are of Learning. Thus little Children
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106454:29"/>were ſaid to enter into Covenant, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.11, 12. to keep Covenant, and to break Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17, 10.14: And the Children of the <hi>Kohothites of a moneth old,</hi> were ſaid to <hi>keep the charge of the Sanctuary,</hi> Numb. 3.28. And <hi>Levi</hi> to pay Tithes in <hi>Abraham,</hi> while he was yet in his Loins, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.9, 10. Doubtleſs, they were ſaid to do theſe things, either becauſe they did them virtually in their Parents, as being morally one with them untill they could chuſe for themſelves: Or elſe, becauſe they were under viſible Circumſtances of being certainly taught by their Parents to do them themſelves, when they ſhould be in the neareſt, and propereſt capacity ſo to do, and to own what their Parents had done on their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half in the mean time, as much as if they had done it in their own Perſons, But for whether of theſe reaſons, or for both, or for any other they were ſaid to do ſuch things while but Children, for the ſame reaſons may little Children while but ſuch, be as truly ſaid to be Diſciples or Learners. And upon one account or other, Children as well as Parents, are called Diſciples, in <hi>Act.</hi> 15.10. Where ſomes urging the neceſſity of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles being Circumciſed after the manner
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106454:30"/>of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that is, to be proſelyted by Circumciſion, is called, a laying a yoak upon the neck of the Diſciples. Seeing then, the manner of <hi>Moſes</hi> was to Circumciſe Proſelytes, both Fathers, and Male Children, and the preſſing the continuance of this among all Gentiles Proſelyted to Chriſtianity, is called, a putting a yoak upon the neck of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples; it is impoſſible to prove but that the Children, as well as the Fathers, are meant by the Diſciples, upon whoſe neck the yoak would have been laid, becauſe it is manifeſt they, as well as their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, were the Perſons, whoſe Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was urged as neceſſary. For theſe reaſons I conclude they will never be able to prove little Children to be no Diſciples: and if not, they can never be able to prove them excluded out of Chriſt's Commiſſion for Baptizing Diſciples.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They cannot prove that the ends of Baptiſm are not attained when Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to Infants of Believing Parents. Firſt, one great end of Baptiſm, is to ſignifie to all Men by viſible ſign and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation, the ſame thing which Gods Covenant in the Goſpel doth by Word. Baptiſm conveys to the mind by the ſenſe of ſeeing, the ſame thing as the word of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106454:30"/>the Goſpel doth by the ſenſe of hearing, which is the Covenant of Salvation, or the terms on which God hath promiſed to ſave Men. Chriſt's Death, Burial, and Reſurrection, as the means by which pardon and Salvation are conditionally obtained for, and promiſed to all Men, are ſignified in Baptiſm. And our dying unto ſin and riſing to a new Life, as the condition upon which that pardon and Salvation are promiſed, are likewiſe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified in Baptiſm. Hence we are ſaid to be buryed with Chriſt in Baptiſm into Death, and to be raiſed with him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. And to be ſaved as by a figure by Baptiſm, as it ſignifies the Reſurrection of Chriſt, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of a good Conſcience, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. And becauſe the ſubſtance of the new Covenant is repreſented in Baptiſm; thence it is that Baptiſm is called the ſign of the Covenant. And becauſe it is an inſtitution of God to aſſure Men that upon the terms ſignified by it, they ſhall be pardoned, and ſaved, thence it is called the Seal of the Covenant, as Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion for the like reaſon was. For Circumciſion was a ſign to ſignifie upon what condition God promiſed Men to be their God, and a Seal to aſſure them that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:106454:31"/>upon their performing that Condition, he would be their God. And the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſignified was Circumciſion in the Spirit, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> expounds it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28, 29. that is, mortification, or the change of the heart, the ſame for ſubſtance with the new Birth, repreſented in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. But then Baptiſm no more than Circumciſion, doth ſignifie that all that have received it, have performed the Condition of the promiſe of Salvation therein ſignified, but to aſſure them and all others, that upon the performance of it, the benefits promiſed ſhall be confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. For the ſign of the Covenant doth not ſignifie more to Men than the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant it ſelf: and the Covenant it ſelf doth not ſignifie to Men that they have performed the Condition of it. As to this end then, as Circumciſion was of a publick and common uſe to the Females as well as the Males, though they were not circumciſed themſelves; ſo is Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm much more both to the Perſons themſelves who are Baptized, and to all others, as well when it is adminiſtred to Children, as when to Men of riper years.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Another end of Baptiſm is to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige the Perſons Baptized to perform the Condition of the Covenant in being born
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:106454:31"/>again, of making them new hearts, and becoming new Creatures, as ever they hope to receive the benefits of pardon and Salvation, promiſed in the Covenant upon that Condition. It is from this Obligation that a holy Life is frequently preſſed upon Chriſtians from their having been Baptized, and that it is called, the <hi>Baptiſm unto Repentance,</hi> Rom. 6. Col. 2 and 3 Chap. Mark 1. And Baptiſm can be no leſs an Obligation to Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and a Holy Life when adminiſtred to Infants, than Circumciſion was in like caſe: and yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever was Circumciſed, was bound to keep the Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. And thoſe Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in their Infancy, if when they come to years of diſcretion, do prove ſuch as make Conſcience of their own perſonal Obligation, they uſually take themſelves to be as much obliged by their Infant-Baptiſm, as they do who are Baptized at years of diſcretion, and diſcharge it as well. All which conſidered, Infant-Baptiſm cannot be proved a Nullity as to this end neither.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Another end of Baptiſm, if it be not the ſame with that before mentioned, is a ſolemn dedication of the perſon Baptized, to the Worſhip and Service of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:106454:32"/>the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, called a being Baptized in the Name, or into the Name of Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. And is not ſuch an Act done by Parents as obliging to their Children, as that of the Jews was when <hi>they took upon them, and decreed for their Seed, that they ſhould keep the dayes of purim?</hi> And as that of <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Parents was in devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to be a <hi>Nazarite</hi> from the womb, <hi>Eſt.</hi> 9.27, 28, 31. <hi>Judges</hi> 16.17. Or, as the Parents Covenant with the <hi>Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> was to their Children after them. Or, as <hi>David</hi>'s and <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s was to their Seed, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.42. Or, as the Fathers Act in Circumciſing his Child, was obliging to the Child afterwards to keep the Law.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Another end and uſe of Baptiſm is ſolemnly to declare ſuch to be of the Church, who are Baptized, and to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their right to Church-priviledges, and as the Chriſtian badge to be a mark of diſtinction between compleat Members of the Church, and thoſe which are not; even as Circumciſion was of old. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are as capable of theſe ends by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, as they formerly were by Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion.</p>
                  <p>If it be ſaid, there may be other ends
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:106454:32"/>of Baptiſm that cannot be attained in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants Baptiſm, as they may in the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of thoſe of riper years: yet, if this be granted, it will not therefore follow, that their Baptiſm is a Nullity, ſo long as other ends of Baptiſm are attained thereby. It might as well be ſaid, that more ends of Circumciſion were attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the Circumciſion of grown Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes than of Minor Proſelytes: but if there were, it did not make their Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion Null. Our Saviour did not by his Perſonal Baptiſm profeſs Repentance and Mortification of any ſin of his, and belief of pardon of it, (as many others did of their ſins in their Baptiſm) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had none to repent of, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, or to be pardoned: and yet I hope none will ſay his Baptiſm was a Nullity. And if the abſence of ſuch a profeſſion did not make his Baptiſm a Nullity, how can it be proved that the abſenee of it will make the Baptiſm of Infants to be a Nullity? The abſence of one end of Baptiſm, doth no more make it uſeleſs as to all other ends, and, conſequently, no more a Nullity, then all ſuch Marriages are Nullities where procreation of Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, which is one end of Marriage, is not attainable.</p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:106454:33"/>
                  <p>Now then, conſidering what hath been ſaid about Infants Church-Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Diſciple-ſhip, and the attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of the ends of Baptiſm in their Baptiſm, I appeal to all who are not over-grown with prejudice and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality, whether ever Infant-Baptiſm be like to be proved to be a Nullity: And if not, whether ſeparation upon ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition that it is, be not a cauſleſs rent in the Church, which is Schiſm in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality of it.</p>
                  <p>But beſides all this, I have another thing in the ſecond place to ſay, and that is, that if Inſant-Baptiſm could be proved an errour, yet it can never be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be an errour of that Nature as will of it ſelf, and without any other cauſe, be a ſufficient ground of ſeparation, as to other Acts of Church-Communion. To make this out, I ſhall take one thing for granted, which I believe very few, if any, of the Anabaptiſts will deny, and that is, that many, at leaſt, of the Pedobaptiſts are godly, both of Men and Women. <hi>They are Sanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called te be Saints, and ſuch as call upon the Name of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord:</hi> and theſe, and ſuch like Characters are Churches deſcribed by in the Epiſtles,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:106454:33"/>which the Apoſtles wrote to them.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. I reaſon thus then: If Pedobap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts are godly Men, ſuch as believe in Chriſt, then they are Members of Chriſt: and if they are Members of Chriſt, they are of his Body, the Church: and if they be of the Church, then they have right to Communion with the Church, and they that deny it them, deny them their right: Becauſe Union with the whole, creates a right to Communion with the parts in all Bodies, Natural, Political, or Myſtical. The Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Goſpel-Ordinances, which is given by Chriſt for the Edification of the whole Body, belongs to every part, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21, 22, 23.</p>
                  <p>If it be ſaid, though ſuch Pedobap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts have a remote right, yet without Baptiſm after Faith they cannot have an immediate right to Church-Communion: I anſwer, that Baptiſm after Faith, can be no more neceſſary to Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, then it is unto Salvation. For the means cannot be more neceſſary to the ſubordinate end which is Church-Communion, then it is to the principal, which is Salvation. And Baptiſm is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation but by way of duty where opportunity occurs, but not by
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:106454:34"/>way of means where opportunity of doing ones duty is wanting. And if to be Baptized after Faith, were indeed the Pedobaptiſts duty, the true reaſon why they do not perform it, is the want of a Moral opportunity, that is, the want of conviction that it is their duty, they verily believing they were ſufficiently Baptized in their Infaucy, and that it is not Lawful for them to be re-baptized. And all the while they remain under this perſwaſion, they can no more lawfully receive an after-baptizing by a voluntary ſubmiſſion to it, then they can who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be Baptized, but want the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of that health, or ſuch an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrator, as is neceſſary thereto. And if their right to Salvation under theſe Circumſtances, be not cut off, as doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, it is not for the reaſon before given, then no more can their right to Church-Communion be thereby cut off for the fame reaſon. I think I may very ſafely ſay, that there is no errour in judgment about Baptiſm, nor about any other thing, which yet is conſiſtent with ſaving Faith and Love, and not pertinaciouſly perſiſted in after conviction, for which a Man can duly be deprived of Church-Communion, that doth not by his volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:106454:34"/>ſeparation deprive himſelf of it: which perſiſting in errour after convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not the caſe of the honeſt-minded Pedobaptiſts, though they ſhould be ſuppoſed to be in errour. Perſons erring upon no worſe terms, are, doubtleſs, the objects of Chriſtian forbearance in the Church, and not of ſuch ſeverity as to exclude them from Communion. This you may take as a further account why I ſaid Baptiſm after Faith can be no more neceſſary to Church-Communion, then it is unto Salvation.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If very many of the Pedobaptiſts are ſuch godly Perſons, and true believers in Chriſt, as are afore deſcribed, then it cannot be denyed but they are ſuch whom the Lord hath received into Communion with himſelf: and if ſo, then thoſe who are likewiſe his People, ought to receive them into their Communion too; <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1-3. <hi>Him that is weak in the faith receive ye, for God hath received him;</hi> Rom. 15.7. <hi>Wherefore receive ye one another, as Chriſt received us.</hi> If it be ſaid, theſe Script<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ures concern ſuch as were duly Baptized: I anſwer, That the reaſon why they ſhould receive one another, is not fetcht from their having been Baptized, but from the Lord's receiving them. And
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:106454:35"/>no ſuppoſed errour in Perſons about Baptiſm, can be a reaſon why they ſhould not be received to Communion, farther then it is a reaſon to prove that the Lord hath not received them. St. <hi>Peter</hi> thought it a good reaſon why the Chriſtians ſhould make no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween believing Jews and believing Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, though they were of different per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions about the neceſſity, and non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſity of Circumciſion (wherein the one erred) becauſe the Lord made no difference, but gave to one the Holy Ghoſt as well as to the other, and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the hearts of the one by Faith as well as the other, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.8, 9. His reaſon is not ſetcht from the Nature of the things wherein they differed, but from God's giving them an equal intereſt in his grace notwithſtanding their difference. When God had vouchſafed the gift of his grace and Spirit to the Gentiles as well as to the Jews, St. <hi>Peter</hi> thought that if after this he ſhould have kept the ſame diſtance from them as before he thought he was bound to do, he ſhould have withſtood God in ſo doing, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.17. <hi>For as much then as God gave them the like gift, as he did unto us, who believed on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; what was I, that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:106454:35"/>I could withſtand God?</hi> To keep at a diſtance from thoſe to whom God draws nigh in the Communication of his grace and Spirit, is, it ſeems, to ſteer a courſe againſt God, or to withſtand him.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Anabaptiſts and Pedobaptiſts, if Godly, do by Faith hold Communion one with another in eating the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual meat, and drinking the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual drink; the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, which is the thing ſignified in the Lord's Supper: <hi>Except ye eat the fleſh of the Son of Man, and drink his blood, ye have no Life in you;</hi> Joh. 6.53. And therefore they cannot duly deny Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them in the Lord's Supper it ſelf, which is the ſign.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe if they do, they thereby croſs one great end and deſign of God in that Ordinance; which is to increaſe and ſtrengthen Love and Unity among Chriſtians in communicating together in the ſign, upon account of their joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intereſt in, and Relation to Chriſt, the Subſtance. Chriſtians by their Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in that Ordinance, are made <hi>to drink into one Spirit,</hi> or, into one-neſs of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. But by their thus refuſing to Communicate one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they do not only ſin in not uſing
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:106454:36"/>the Lord's appointed means to increaſe and ſtrengthen Love and Unity upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of common intereſt in the ſame Saviour, but alſo in that by ſuch their refuſal, they deſtroy Unity, and weaken &amp; diminiſh Love: they pull down inſtead of building up, ſteer a contrary courſe to Chriſt in appointing that Ordinance.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Men's right to the ſign, proceeds upon the beſt account from their right to the thing ſignified, though not from that only. As thoſe who have right to ſuch or ſuch an Eſtate in Land, have thereby a right to the deeds and evidences by which ſuch a right is to be declared: So thoſe that have a right to the Body and Blood of Chriſt through Faith, have thereby a right to the Lord's Supper, as an evidence appointed by God, by which ſuch their right is to be declared and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged. And therefore as a detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch evidence from him who by having right to the Land, hath right to the evidence, would be an injury: even ſo for any as much as in them lies to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Lord's Supper from them who by having right to the Body and Blood of Chriſt, have right to the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per as an evidence and ſign thereof, would be an injury likewiſe, and that ſo much
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:106454:36"/>greater too, as Spiritual things are of more value then temporal.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It is abſurd, and againſt common reaſon for them to grant that the Godly Pedobaptiſts have Communion with them in the greater and better part, and yet for a ſuppoſed errour conſiſtent with ſaving Faith &amp; Love, to deny it them in the leſs, whenas the greater alwayes includes the leſs. But for the Godly Pedobaptiſts to be partakers of like precious Faith with them, and thereby to eat of that Fleſh which is meat indeed, and to drink of that Blood which is drink indeed, together with themſelves (a thing which the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts will not deny) is certainly to have, hold, and enjoy Communion with them in the greater, better, more Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, and more ſubſtantial part of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; and therefore to deny it them in the out-ſide and letter of it, which is far leſs conſiderable, is very incongruous and contradictious.</p>
                  <p>What was objected by diſtinguiſhing between an immediate and remote right, if it ſhould be here brought in again, hath been anſwered before, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer need not be repeated, but only apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here. And let it be remembred alwayes, that there is a vaſt difference between
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:106454:37"/>thoſe who deny, and thoſe that hold the neceſſity and uſefulneſs of water Baptiſm in theſe latter Ages of the Church. The Pedobaptiſts are as much for water-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, as the Anabaptiſts are, and hold themſelves as firmly engaged by their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm, as they do by their after-Baptiſm. If this were not ſo, their caſe would not be ſo pleadable as now it is.</p>
                  <p>And for any to ſeparate from them upon account of their being Baptized in their Infancy, as it is without ground from Scripture, I conceive, ſo it is without all preſident in the Church of Chriſt for the firſt fifteen hundred years and more. Though ſome in the ancient Church were Baptized in Infancy, and ſome at Age, yet there was never any breaking of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion among them upon that ſcore ſo far as ever I could learn, untill a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of a Reformation was ſet on foot; the one to puzle and confound the other: I mean, the attempt of the Anabaptiſts in <hi>Germany</hi> to Reform the Reformation by <hi>Luther</hi> and others. Which may be a motive to reflect upon what they have done, and to review their grounds. Can they think to out-do the Church in her pureſt times in point of Communion?
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:106454:37"/>Me-thinks they ſhould greatly ſuſpect themſelves in their undertaking wherein they go ſo manifeſtly contrary to the Univerſal Church in all places and Ages till ſo lately, as afore-ſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="dividing_principle">
                  <head>II. <hi>Dividing Principle to be avoided.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>That it is unlawful to hold Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with parochial Congregations, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they have been Baptized into the Profeſſion of the true Faith, and continue in that profeſſion. This is another grand dividing Principle indeed. They who hold this, and practice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, muſt prove ſuch Communion unlawful, or elſe lye under the guilt of a ſinful Schiſm, or cauſleſs ſeparation, and of all the evil and miſchievous effects and conſequences of it. And to prove it unlawful, they muſt prove it is ſo, either by proving, 1. That all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of each Parochial Aſſembly from which they ſeparate, are deſtitute of ſaving grace; or, 2. By proving that the mixture of bad with good, makes Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion unlawful; or, 3. By proving the conſtitution of ſuch Congregations bad, upon account of that diſtribution by which the whole Nation is divided into
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:106454:38"/>its parts and precincts; or, 4. By pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the worſhip in thoſe Aſſemblies, to be ſuch as may not lawfully be joyned in. Theſe contain either all, or the principal pretended cauſes of a ſtated ſeparation from them. For the plea upon account of the inſufficiency of ſome Miniſters, is a thing but of an accidental Nature, and no Univerſal pretence of ſeparation. And whether they are like to prove all, or indeed any of theſe, you may pleaſe to conſider what follows, and then judge.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They cannot prove all the members of each parochial Aſſembly from which they ſeparate, to be deſtitute of ſaving grace, much leſs to be ſo ſcandalous as to deſerve Excommunication. For,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, there is ſo little a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween common grace, and the loweſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of ſpecial and ſaving grace, as makes it impoſſible for one Chriſtian to know another to be deſtitute of ſaving grace, the tenor of whoſe Life is not worſe then theirs, who are the moſt inoffenſive and beſt diſpoſed in the Pariſhes. And if they cannot make proof that they are all deſtitute of ſaving grace; then,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Its utterly againſt the rules of Charity, indeed of all Chriſtianity, to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:106454:38"/>judge ſuch to be deſtitute of ſaving grace, of which they cannot make certain proof. For <hi>Charity thinketh no evil,</hi> but <hi>believeth all things, and hopeth all things.</hi> And for one Man to judge another to have no grace, or to be in a damnable condition who is not manifeſtly guilty of living in ſuch ſins as for which the Script<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure expreſly excludes Men out of the Kingdome of Heaven, is a thing which the Scripture expreſly condemns as a great ſin. Mat. 7.1. <hi>Judge not, that ye be not judged.</hi> Jam. 4.12. <hi>Who art thou that judgeſt another?</hi> And again, <hi>Who art thou that judgeſt another mans Servant?</hi> Rom. 14.4. And can they prove indeed (or will they undertake it) that all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of this or that Pariſh without exception, are guilty of ſuch ſins, as for which the Scripture doth expreſly bar Men out of the Kingdome of Heaven. And if not, dare they judge them all to be in a reprobate or damnable condition? And if they dare not, or cannot judge ſo without manifeſt breach of Charity, then to be ſure they cannot prove that they are ſo: And if they cannot prove it, what a horrid thing is it, or would it be to judge whole Pariſhes by the lump to be ſuch?</p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:106454:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:106454:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:106454:40"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:106454:40"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:106454:41"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:106454:41"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:106454:42"/>
                  <p n="3">3. I querie how they will prove it is of abſolute neceſſity unto Lawful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with a Congregation that have been Baptized into one Body the Church, that at leaſt ſome of them ſhould be ſavingly holy? As Suppoſe the Church of <hi>Laodicea</hi> for inſtance had conſiſted all of ſuch as had only a form of Godlineſs; will they ſay, and prove it when they have done, that Communion with them had been unlawful? I ſuppoſe they will not, and am confident they cannot.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They cannot prove that a mixture of the bad with the good makes Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with ſuch mixt Aſſemblies unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. They can neither prove it by Scripture prohibition, nor by Scripture Example.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Let them ſhew where the Scripture forbids it. If they ſay there, where it ſaith, <hi>If any Man that is called a Brother be a Fornicator, or Covetous, or an Idolator, or a railer, or a drunkard, or an Extortioner, with ſuch an one no, not to eat;</hi> 1 Cor. 5.11. And where again it ſaith, <hi>Withdraw your ſelves from every Brother that walks diſord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly, and the like.</hi> The Anſwer is ready, which is this; That theſe, and all other Scriptures of like Nature, are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, either firſt, as injunctions upon
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:106454:42"/>the Church as inveſted with the power of diſcipline; or, ſecondly, as commands to particular Perſons a part. So far as they belong to the Church in a publick capacity, and as inveſted with the power of diſcipline, they impoſe the duty of uſing the power of the Keyes for the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Cure of the ſcandalous, and for preventing contagion in the Church. But ſo far as they reſpect Perſons in a ſingle and private capacity, they prohibit perſonal familiarity and converſe thereby to diſcountenance their evil, and to work them to a ſenſe of it, and to caution others againſt it; and to ſecure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the infection of it. But then there is a vaſt difference between abſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from a perſonal familiarity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with ſuch, and a withdrawing from the Church for the ſake of ſuch: this is a ſin, but the other a duty.</p>
                  <p>And whereas ſome have alledged the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Come out from among them,</hi> &amp;c. This was no call to the better ſort of Chriſtians to ſeparate from the worſer, and ſuch as were ſcandalous in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> but a call to thoſe that had in part embraced the Goſpel, to come quite off from Heatheniſh Idols, and from participating in the Sacrifices
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:106454:43"/>which were offered to them: which is meant by <hi>touch not the unclean thing,</hi> there. This appears by the Context from ver. 14. and by comparing here with, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.7.10. and 10.7.14.21.22.</p>
                  <p>Others alledge, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.4. Come out of her my People, &amp;c. If this be meant of Myſtical <hi>Babylor,</hi> as they underſtand it; It is not a call to ſeparate from thoſe that Worſhip the true God only, and in the Mediation of Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus only, as the Pariſh Churches Proteſtant do; But from her who is ſtiled a Harlot, becauſe ſhe gives that Honour which is due only to God, and to our only Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator Chriſt Jeſus, to Creatures and to other Mediators together with God and with Chriſt. When it can be proved our Pariſh Churches do ſo, then, and not till then, will this Text be pertinently al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to juſtifie ſeparation from them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Let them ſhew, if they can, ſome approved Example in Scripture of ſuch a practice. That there have been great ſcandals in the Churches, both in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the Old Teſtament, and thoſe recorded in the New, is manifeſt, as is ſhewed particularly and at large by Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his fifth <hi>Direct. for Cure of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:106454:43"/>Church-diviſions.</hi> But where do we find any of the better ſort in thoſe Churches, withdrawing themſelves from the more carnal part, into ſeparate Bodies, for Reformation ſake? We read indeed of ſome that <hi>went out from the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not of them;</hi> and of ſome that did <hi>ſeparate themſelves being ſenſual, not having the Spirit;</hi> but not a word of the good ſeparating from the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the bad in it. In the Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> which <hi>had a Name to live, but was dead,</hi> there were but <hi>a few Names,</hi> but what had <hi>defiled their Garments.</hi> And thoſe few indeed are commanded, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by promiſe of great reward for that they had kept their Garments unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed amidſt ſuch a Society, but not in the leaſt encouraged to ſeparate from them, though all the reſt were defiled.</p>
                  <p>They plead indeed, that particular Churches ought to conſiſt of none but of viſible Saints, becauſe this is agreeable to the primitive patern: the appellations or Titles which are given the Churches in the Epiſtles the Apoſtles wrote to them, declare them to have been ſuch when they ſay <hi>to the Saints in ſuch and ſuch a place.</hi> This is not denyed, but the Queſtion is upon what account they were eſteemed
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:106454:44"/>viſible Saints, and were ſo ſtyled? As whether it were, 1. Becauſe there were ſuch ſpecial poſitive ſigns of ſaving grace beſides their common profeſſion of Chriſtianity viſible in all the Members of thoſe Churches, as that there was juſt cauſe they ſhould be ſtiled Saints upon that account? Or, 2. Whether the whole were not denominated from the better part? Or, 3. Whether it was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were all Saints by an outward Calling and Profeſſion.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It is no wayes probable they had all ſuch poſitive ſigns of ſaving Sanctity upon them, as that they were all ſtiled Saints upon that account. Sure it was not for this cauſe that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtiled thoſe of the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1. When at the ſame time he ſaith there was <hi>ſuch Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among them as was not ſo much as named among the Heathen.</hi> Chap. 5.1. that there were ſome of them, <hi>that with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the Idol did eat of the Sacrifice offered to it,</hi> Chap. 8.7. that at the Lord's Supper <hi>ſome were hungry, and ſome drunk,</hi> for which with other profanations of it, many of them had been viſited with ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Death, Chap. 11. that <hi>ſome among them had not the knowledge of God,</hi>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:106454:44"/>and <hi>did deny the Reſurrection,</hi> Chap. 15. that <hi>he feared that when he ſhould come among them, he ſhould not find them ſuch as he would, but that he ſhould find debates, envyings, wraths, ſtrifes, back bitings, whiſperings, ſwellings, tumults among them, and ſome that had not repented of the uncleanneſs, and Fornication, and laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs which they had committed;</hi> 2 Cor. 12.20, 21. Theſe things according to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s account, in <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21. were rather ſigns of ſuch as ſhall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Kingdome of God then of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace. I doubt thoſe who plead the primitive patern for admitting none into their ſeparate Churches but who are under poſitive ſigns of ſaving grace, would be unwilling to receive ſuch for viſible Saints as here we have found among thoſe to whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> writes as to Saints. But if Perſons under ſuch Characters as aforeſaid, paſſed with St. <hi>Paul</hi> for viſible Saints upon one account or other, how comes it to paſs that thoſe of our Pariſhes that make the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion as the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> did, will not paſs for viſible Saints too upon the ſame account, be it what it will? Is it becauſe they are under worſe Characters then thoſe already mentioned? I trow
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:106454:45"/>not, but rather becauſe they are partial that ſtick at it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If they will ſay they were all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominated Saints from the better part among them in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> and other Churches, then why may not our parochial Congregations be ſo too? Unleſs they will ſay there is none good among them, and prove what they ſay, which to be ſure they can never do, if they had hearts to attempt it. But this cannot be the reaſon why they are called Saints, becauſe theſe two phraſes, <hi>the Church of God which is at</hi> Corinth, <hi>and the Sanctified in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> are of equal latitude and extent, and both refer to all the ſame perſons, as appears by the words them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which are theſe. <hi>Unto the Church of God which is at</hi> Corinth, <hi>to them that are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called to be Saints:</hi> the latter words being exegeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal of the former, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If they were ſtyled Saints upon account of their external Calling by which they were ſeparated from the Pagan and Infidel World and Worſhip, unto a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed belief in, and obedience to the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, into which they had been Baptized, then our parochial Congregations conſiſt of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:106454:45"/>viſible Saints too as well as thoſe: For they have been Baptized into the ſame Faith, and continue to profeſs it: And by that profeſſion are ſeparated from the Infidel and Pagan World. So that let our Opponents in this point take it in which ſenſe they will, yet they will never be able to prove but that our Parochical Congregations are viſible Saints upon the ſame account, and in the ſame ſenſe, in which thoſe of the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> were ſtiled Saints.</p>
                  <p>And it is moſt probable that the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Churches were ſtiled Saints upon this laſt mentioned account of an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward calling and profeſſion of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Saints with them ſignified but the ſame thing as Chriſtians now doth with us, and was the common appellation by which the profeſſors of Chriſtianity were diſtinguiſhed from others then, as Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian is now. Where they were once called Chriſtians then, they were twenty times called Saints, if we may eſtimate their uſage by what is recorded. For we have the appellation Saints above threeſcore times in the New Teſtament, and that of Chriſtian but thrice, as I take it. They were called Saints, as it is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. For the two words [to be]
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:106454:46"/>are added by the Tranſlators in both places. You will never find I ſuppoſe the appellation, Saints, applyed to the ſincere in oppoſition to the unſincere of the Church, as by Cuſtome now they are, but alwayes in oppoſition to thoſe that were not at all of the Church, or which made no profeſſion of Chriſtianity at all. It was, I take it, in this ſenſe; &amp; by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of an outward Calling and Profeſſion, that thoſe were ſaid to be <hi>Sanctified by the blood of the Covenant,</hi> who yet by Apoſtacy <hi>trod under foot the Son of God, and counted that Blood an unholy thing;</hi> Heb. 10.29. All that were outwardly called ſo far as to profeſs Chriſtianity, were called to be Saints, Saints by Calling. Our Saviour hath told us over and over, that many are called, and but few are choſen: its well if there be not abundantly more nominal then real Saints. The whole Body of the People of the Jews by virtue of an external Calling to Worſhip the true God, and to receive and obſerve his Law, were called <hi>Saints,</hi> and a <hi>Holy People unto the Lord,</hi> Deut. 33.2, 3. and 7.6. And a Congregation of ſuch are called a <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Saints,</hi> and Aſſemblies of ſuch, <hi>Aſſemblies of Saints,</hi> Pſal. 89.5.7. and 149.1. And yet we know what ſorry
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:106454:46"/>Saints many of them appeared to be. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems to reckon the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> and other Churches to conſiſt of ſomewhat alike mixture as that of the Jews of old did, when he told them that they were Types of us upon whom the ends of the World are come, and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed them by God's ſore diſpleaſure ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed againſt moſt of them: And would by no means have them ignorant or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindful of one thing, and that was, that thoſe with whom God was not well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but overthrew them in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, were of God's Church, and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſpecial priviledges, as well as they themſelves: which priviledges he expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in terms more appropriate to their preſent Chriſtian ſtate, when he ſaith, they were all Baptized unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> and did all eat the ſame Spiritual meat, and drank the ſame Spiritual drink. By whoſe example he would have them take warning, and not be flattered into a good opinion of themſelves meerly upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Baptiſm and holding Communion with the Church in Holy Adminiſtrations, and being numbred among the Saints or Chriſtians; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. And truly they ſeem to be much more in danger of being betrayed into
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:106454:47"/>ſuch a ſelf-flattery, who are not admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Church-fellowſhip upon their Chriſtian profeſſion, unleſs beſides that they can give ſuch a ſatisfactory account to the Church of their converſion after they have been firſt received into the Church Catholique by Baptiſm, in which there may be great miſtake in them that ſo receive them. And therefore the <hi>New-England</hi> Miniſters in their Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Davenport's</hi> Apologetical Preface, <hi>p.</hi> 43, 44. ſay thus: <hi>Indeed when Men confound theſe two, and do tye viſible Church-Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-ſhip unto ſuch Conditions and qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as are reputed enough to Salvation: this may tend to harden Men, and to make them conceit, that if once they be got into the Church, they are ſure of Heaven; whenas alas, it may be they are far from it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But in all this there is nothing againſt the great uſefulneſs and defirableneſs of Diſcipline in the Church, for the Cure or Excommunication of the notoriouſly ſcandalous. But yet a neglect of this in them to whom it belongs, is no ſufficient ground of ſeparation from that Church where it is ſo neglected. For though Diſcipline be neceſſary for the better being of the Church, yet it is not of the Eſſence of the Church: it doth not ceaſe
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:106454:47"/>to be a true Church for want of it. And the neglect of it in a Church is ſo far from being a reaſon why the better part in ſuch a Church ſhould ſeparate from the worſe, as that it is indeed a reaſon againſt it why they ſhould not: Becauſe where publick Diſcipline is wanting, there is the more need of private application to delinquent Members, which ſeparation takes Men off from, or at beſt puts them under a great diſadvantage of doing that good among them thereby, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they might. Such a ſeparation ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther puts thoſe ſeparated from, under a temptation of Making a party againſt them, as is frequently ſeen: and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion made and heightened thus on both ſides, tends more to weaken the Chriſtian Intereſt in the main, then all the exerciſe of Diſcipline in ſeparate Congregations, tends to promote it. Its true, if Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians were to mind only the pleaſing of themſelves, it would be a pleaſant thing for the good indeed to converſe and hold Communion with ſuch only as themſelves. But it will turn to a better account at laſt, if by denying their inclination in this they help and bring on a worſer ſort, and <hi>gain their Maſter ten Talent.</hi> There ſhould <hi>be more abundant honour given to that part
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:106454:48"/>which lacketh, that there may be no Schiſm in the Body,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.24. Our Saviour himſelf was chiefly for the bringing home of ſtraying <hi>Sheep,</hi> and as a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian to be among the ſick rather then the whole: Not becauſe he loved them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; but becauſe they had more need, and becauſe he could thereby be more ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as to the main end of his coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World. <hi>He came not to call the Righteous, but ſinners to Repentance: to miniſter, and not to be miniſtred to.</hi> And to be this way employed, ſeems to be more acceptable to God, then to have to do only with the Righteous: <hi>There is joy in Heaven over one ſinner that repenteth, more then over ninety and nine juſt Perſons which need no Repentance.</hi> And thus much I think may ſuffice to ſhew how unlikely, yea, how impoſſible it is to prove that the mixture of the bad with the good in the Pariſhes, makes Communion with them unlawful.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They cannot prove the conſtitution of parochial Congregations to be bad up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on account of that diſtribution by which the whole Nation is divided into parts, into ſo many Pariſhes, which they are wont to call humane inſtitution. For, firſt, they are of the ſame inſtitution in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:106454:48"/>the main, as thoſe were which were plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Apoſtles themſelves. For from what were thoſe called Churches, but from the Chriſtians uſual Aſſembling together for Communion in Goſpel-Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances? The Greek word Tranſlated <hi>Church</hi> properly ſignifying an <hi>Aſſembly.</hi> And if the Pariſhioners in a Pariſh, do uſually Aſſemble together upon the ſame account, are not thoſe Goſpel-Churches as well as the other? and of the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution?</p>
                  <p>Secondly, for the Chriſtians that live within the ſame Precincts or Pariſh-bounds to Aſſemble together for Communion in Goſpel-Ordinances, and ſo to be of the ſame particular Church, and not of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is a thing which beſt anſwers the ends of particular Church-ſhip, and the primitive patern. For vicinity of Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour-hood and cohabitation, (which generally are not to be had ſo well in any other way as in that of parochial diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution) do beſt accommodate thoſe in Church-Relation, with the knowledge of each others Condition and Converſation, and with opportunity and advantage to watch over, confer with, and to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, exhort and comfort one another, and to Aſſemble together for publick
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:106454:49"/>Worſhip; which are the ends of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church-aſſociation. And accordingly the primitive Chriſtians which lived to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether within the ſame civil bounds of Cities and Towns, as of <hi>Corinth, Cenchrea,</hi> &amp;c. were conſtantly of the ſame Church, and as ſuch were ſtill denominated by the places where they did reſide. And if ſome ſuch diſtribution of the Chriſtians in a Nation into ſeveral particular Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping Congregations as is now made by humane Authority, is neceſſary of it ſelf in reference to the Church-Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though no humane Authority had required it, then certainly the command of humane Authority that it ſhould be ſo, cannot make it unneceſſary, much leſs unlawful.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. They cannot prove the Worſhip now uſed in our parochial Aſſemblies, to be ſuch as may not lawfully be joyned in. The Lawfulneſs of Communion in the Worſhip of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lyturgy, is the thing in queſtion. And if they cannot prove Communion in it unlawful, neither, 1. Becauſe it is a ſet Form; nor, 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſuch a ſet Form as it is; nor, 3. Becauſe it is impoſed; then I ſhall take it for granted they cannot prove it unlawful any other way. And whether
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:106454:49"/>ever they are like to prove Communion in that Worſhip unlawful upon any of thoſe accounts, conſider what I have to offer, and then judge.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They cannot prove Communion in that Worſhip unlawful upon account of its being a ſet Form; becauſe they cannot prove all ſet Forms of Worſhip fotbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. We have Prayer ſeveral times com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in Scripture, but no where de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined that it ſhall be extemporary that ever I could learn. And therefore if the want of an expreſs precept for praying in a ſet Form made praying in a ſet Form unlawful, the ſame thing would make ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary prayer unlawful too. When God hath in Scripture plainly determined to whom we ſhall pray, and in whoſe Name, and for what, and in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but not in what external mode, as whether in a ſet Form or without; either of them may be Lawful. For the reaſon, doubtleſs, why God hath not reſtrained Prayer either to the one mode or the other, is, that either may be made uſe of as occaſion ſerves, or circumſtances re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. For if he had not intended to have left Men at more Liberty in this then he hath in the object, matter, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of prayer, he would have been as
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:106454:50"/>particular in determining in what mode he would be ſought to, as in what Name, and for what. It is in this duty of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in reference to the mode, much as it is in the duty of ſinging of Pſalms: the duty of ſinging them is expreſly enjoyned in the New Teſtament as well as the Old, but what Pſalms in particular, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch as are indited by them that ſing, or by ſome others for them, or whether in Proſe or in Meeter, or whether by all the Congregation joyntly, or by a part only, are circumſtances not determined particularly in the New Teſtament. And why are they not? But that there might be a Liberty left to vary in theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars as circumſtances ſhould render it moſt convenient. Some indeed have made ſuch ill uſe of this, as that becauſe the Scripture hath not determined all theſe particulars, they will not make uſe of any, and ſo wholly neglect the duty it ſelf, to the diſhonour of him who hath made it a duty: as if he had been defective in not determining thoſe circumſtances, when as Men were purpoſely left at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty herein for their greater edification. And doubtleſs for the ſame reaſon is the external mode of Prayer left ſo much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determined as it is.</p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:106454:50"/>
                  <p>By theſe things we may ſee how impertinently ſome uſe to object againſt the Lyturgical mode of Worſhip, the ſin of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> in offering ſtrange fire before the Lord, and of <hi>Jeroboam's</hi> keeping the Paſſeover on the fifteenth day of the eighth Moneth, and the like. For if the offering of Incenſe had been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, but with what fire not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, it would not have been their ſin to have offered with any fire that had been conveniently uſeful for that purpoſe. And ſo if the keeping of the Paſſeover had been commanded, and neither time nor place determined, it would have been no ſin to have kept it on the fifteenth day of the eighth Moneth, and in <hi>Bethel,</hi> provided it had been to the Lord only. So we ſay when Prayer is commanded, but the mode not determined, any are lawful as Circumſtances ſhall render them convenient. God had appointed with what fire Incenſe ſhould be offered as well as that Incenſe it ſelf ſhould be offered, <hi>viz.</hi> with fire from off the Altar: And ſo he had in what Moneth, and on what day of the Moneth the Paſſeover ſhould be kept, as well as that it ſhould be kept at all: and in varying from theſe was the ſin of thoſe Men. If God had limitted
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:106454:51"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:106454:51"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:106454:52"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:106454:52"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:106454:53"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:106454:53"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:106454:54"/>Prayer by his command to that mode which we call extemporary praying, then theſe inſtances would have been perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently alledged againſt the Lyturgy, but this is not the caſe; and therefore they, and all other of like Nature are imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently alledged againſt modes of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip not determined in Scripture either one way or other. And ſuch is the alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of thoſe Scriptures alſo in this caſe, which are againſt adding to the Word, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.32. againſt Sacrificing to Idol-gods, which God ſaith he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded not, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.31. and 19.5. <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.3. againſt making falſe repreſentations of God by Images, as in the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, which becauſe they do ſo, are therefore called a lye: all which refer to falſe Worſhip in the ſubſtance of it, as being contrary to God's expreſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and not unto ſuch circumſtances relating to the ſubſtance of Commanded Worſhip, which are neither Commanded nor forbidden, but left to the prudence of God's People to order themſelves in by general Rules: for which cauſe the allegation of them in this buſineſs, is wholly impertinent and irrelative to the queſtion. And yet this way of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applying Scripture, hath been, I think
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:106454:54"/>I may ſay, the only way of upholding unlawful ſeparations in the Church.</p>
                  <p>But the plain truth is, if that would ſatisfie Men, that the Scripture is ſo far from forbidding the uſe of a ſet Form in Prayer in any caſe, as that there is much in the Scripture to countenance it. God Commanded a Form to be uſed by the Prieſts in Bleſſing the People, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.23. — <hi>Hezekiah the King, and the Princes commanded the Levites to ſing praiſe unto the Lord with the words of</hi> David <hi>and</hi> Aſaph <hi>the Seer,</hi> 2 Chron. 29.30. What are many of the Pſalms but ſo many ſet Forms of Prayer and Thankſgiving? The Title of the 102 Pſalm, is <hi>A Prayer for the afflicted when he is over-whelmed and poureth out his complaint before the Lord.</hi> The 72 Pſalm concludes thus, <hi>The prayers of</hi> David, <hi>the Son of</hi> Jeſſe, <hi>are ended.</hi> The Title of the 90 Pſalm is a Prayer of <hi>Moſes</hi> the man of God. Our Saviour taught his Diſciples a Forme of Prayer, as <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> had before taught his; and commanded them ſaying, <hi>when ye Pray, ſavour Father.</hi> &amp;c. And is it not ſtrange then that any of his Diſciples ſhould ſay when ye pray, ſay not our Father, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Again, do not they who ſing Pſalms
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:106454:55"/>pray to God, and praiſe God in a ſet Form? Nay, is not the Prayer of every Miniſter a Form to all the People that joyn with him, how extemporary ſoever it may be to him himſelf? For they are as much confined in this caſe, as if he read it out of a Book: and every time he va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, it is ſtill but a new Form to the People. So that they that are moſt againſt Forms, are neceſſitated to uſe ſome themſelves. And ſo I have done with ſhewing my reaſon why the Prayers of the Lyturgie cannot be proved unlawful in reſpect of its being a ſet Form.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They cannot prove it unlawful to joyn in the Prayers made according to the Lyturgie upon account of its being ſuch a ſet Form as it is; Neither, 1. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the object to whom, nor of the Mediator by whom the Prayer is made. Nor, 2. In reſpect of the matter of it of which it doth conſiſt. Nor, 3. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the words and phraſe ſignificant of the matter. Nor, 4. In reſpect of the method, the repetitions, the abrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the reſponſes, or popular concla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations thereby uſed, nor becauſe read out of a Book. Nor, 5. Though they ſhould be able to prove the fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned repetitions, abruptions, reſponſes,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:106454:55"/>and conclamations, or the like, to be real defects in that mode of Worſhip, and that a better is deſirable, and that another might be more uſeful.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They cannot prove Communion in thoſe Prayers unlawful in reſpect of him to whom they are made, nor in reſpect of him in whoſe Name they are made. For they are made to the true God only, and only in the Name and Mediation of the only Mediatour Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Nor ſecondly, in reſpect of the matter of which they do conſiſt. I know no Prayer in the Lyturgie appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the ordinary publick Worſhip, but what refers either to confeſſion of ſin, or petition for pardon, or for the aſſiſtance of God's grace and Holy Spirit, or for ſome temporal, or other ſpiritual, or eternal Bleſſings, or for the averting of the contrary evils, or to thankſgiving to God for benefits relating to this Life, or that which is to come; and all this in the behalf of our ſelves and others. And if there be nothing but what is of this Nature, the matter of the Prayers to be ſure, cannot be proved to be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They cannot prove Communion in thoſe Prayers unlawful upon account of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:106454:56"/>the words and phraſe by which the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial matter of the Worſhip is expreſſed. They are not made in an unknown tongue or Language not underſtood by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Nor will they ever be able to prove but that in reſpect of the words and phraſe, that mode of Prayer is of the common Nature of any right mode of Prayer whatſoever. The beſt mode of publick Prayer is but a <hi>medium</hi> of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying the ſubſtantial matter of Prayer to the underſtanding and affection of them that pray, and from thence to God. It is neceſſary indeed in this reſpect that the words and phraſe ſhould be ſignificant and expreſſive of the import of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſubſtance of which the Prayer doth conſiſt. As when God is to be magnified for the glory of his perfections and marvellous doings: and when we would be humbled for the pravity and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generateneſs of our Nature and miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages towards him; and when in the ſenſe thereof, and of God's declared goodneſs through Chriſt, we would beg forgiveneſs of ſin and the aſſiſtance of his grace for amendment, and eternal Life in the iſſue, or any temporal Bleſſing; it is neceſſary that theſe things be expreſſed in words and phraſes that have ſome aptneſs in
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:106454:56"/>them to fill the Soul with apprehenſions and affections ſuitable to the reſpective matter of the parts of Prayer to which they do relate. The general Nature of all right modes of Prayer conſiſts in this, whether with, or without the uſe of a Book, whether uttered in a ſet Form of words, or from the preſent invention and conception of the mind. And it cannot with any colour of reaſon or truth be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, but that the Lyturgical mode of Prayer is of this Nature. The words and phraſe are intelligibly ſignificant of the matter and ſubſtance of Prayer to which they relate; and ſo ſerve for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick edification, according to the Rule, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.9.14, 15.</p>
                  <p>And if ſo, then we may, if the fault be not in our ſelves, and if a heart be not wanting, ſeriouſly and devoutly preſent our neceſſary Confeſſions, Petitions, and Thankſgivings unto God in that mode. It is too groſs an apprehenſion of God to think that a greater variety of words and phraſes as ſuch, do delight him: but it is Humilite, Reverence, ſenſe of wants, fervent deſires of ſupply, and faith of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance through Chriſt concurring with words ſignificant of ſuch things, whether pronounced out of a Book, or otherwiſe,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:106454:57"/>that he is pleaſed with. Nor is it comely for us to think that it is the repetition of the ſame words every day, as in the Lord's Prayer, that doth diſpleaſe the Lord: but it is the irreverent, raſh, careleſs, and cuſtomary pouring out words before him without any due ſenſe of what they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, that doth offend him. If Men be but attentive and careful to engage their hearts to go along with the matter ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the words, and to be duly affected with the import thereof; it is not their being read out of a Book that will make theſe Prayers unacceptable or ineffectual: As on the other hand, if Men are careleſs and unconſcionable therein, it is not its proceeding from a gift of him that utters the Prayer that will make it acceptable and effectual, how excellent ſoever the matter and words may be. I conclude then that the mode of Prayer in our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Lyturgie, doth in the general Nature and quality of it, agree with all right modes of publick Prayer whatſoever, and with the general Rule by which all right modes of Prayer are to be ſquared. The queſtion is not whether it be the beſt, but whether it is ſo competently uſeful, as to render Communion in Prayer by it lawful.</p>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:106454:57"/>
                  <p n="4">4. They cannot prove Communion in the Prayers of the Lyturgie unlawful in reſpect of the method, repetitions, abruptions, reſponſes, or conclamations thereby uſed. For ſo long as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in which the duty of Prayer is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, have not determined whether it ſhall be with the help of a Book, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out: or whether longer or ſhorter: or whether all the publick Prayer meet for the Aſſembly ſhall be put up to God in two or three Prayers, or more: or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all ſhall be pronounced by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter only, or part by the People alſo: or whether kneeling or ſtanding; I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee how it will be proved unlawful to do it any of theſe wayes, as circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the caſe may be. For the queſtion before us is not at all which is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient where Men are at Liberty to chuſe, but only what is Lawful, or which is to be choſen under a neceſſity of either uſing ſuch a mode, or of ſeparating. It is not unlawful for all the People in a Congregation to pray to God, or praiſe him together with one voyce, in ſinging of Pſalms: and how then it will be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved unlawful for them to do it in another way of praying, I know not. We read of many that by their conjunction of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:106454:58"/>voyces, <hi>were as one to make one ſound to be heard in praiſing and thanking the Lord,</hi> 2 Chron. 5.13. They may, perhaps, think ſuch repetitions of the ſame Prayer as are uſed by the Lyturgie may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by our Saviour, when he ſaid, when ye Pray uſe not vain repetitions as the Heathen do, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. But they will hardly prove it, if they do but conſider what the vain repetitions which the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then uſed, were. For there ſeems to be no likeneſs or proportion between the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions in the Lyturgie and thoſe of the Heathen. For they repeated the very ſame words it may be a hundred times over and more in a little time: as they, in 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.26. who <hi>from Morning untill Noon, cryed, O</hi> Baal, <hi>hear us; O</hi> Baal, <hi>hear us.</hi> The very ſame words are uſed twenty ſix times in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136. and often in many other Pſalms, and yet I dare not ſay they are a vain repetion, and I ſuppoſe, nor they neither.
<note n="*" place="margin">If ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without expectation of accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance meerly for much ſpeaking, which makes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition vain.</note> It is ſaid of our Saviour, that <hi>again he went away and prayed, and ſpake the ſame words,</hi> Mark 14.39.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Although they ſhould be able cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, and without all doubt to prove the fore-mentioned repetitions, abrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, reſponſes, and conclamations, or
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:106454:58"/>the like, to be real defects in that mode of Worſhip, and that a better <hi>medium</hi> is deſirable, and that another might be more uſeful; yet it will not from thence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that that would be a ſufficient ground or cauſe of ſeparation from the ſubſtance of the Worſhip it ſelf, for theſe two reaſons.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe thoſe who count the uſe of theſe a diſorderly way of praying, need not be active in thoſe things unleſs they will, but only paſſive. And if they be but paſſive, they will not by their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence be guilty of the diſorder. I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they do not think their preſence at conceived prayers by habit, makes them guilty of all the diſorders and defects that are found in them, or ſome of them, ſo long as they do not in their minds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to thoſe diſorders and defects, but are ſorry for them. For they are in ſuch caſes but involuntary defect as to them: and defects of that Nature our beſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances are more or leſs lyable to. We may lay aſide all duties at this rate, if we think we may not endeavour a perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of them till we can do them without all involuntary defects. But that in which a mans will is not, is not morally the mans act: <hi>Every Man is tempted when he
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:106454:59"/>is drawn away of his own luſt, and enticed. Jam.</hi> 1. And no Man is to be counted a conſenter to all that is done in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, though he do not declare his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, unleſs he declare his conſent to it ſome other way then meerly by his preſence. If this were not ſo, a Man would be guilty of all the defects he perceives in the Miniſters Praying and Preaching, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he declared his diſſent from them in the open Congregation, which if practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, would tend to open confuſion. When we conſider the corrupt Eſtate of the Jewiſh Church in which our Saviour held Communion both in Temple-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Synagogue-Worſhip at <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,</hi> where he was brought up; I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe no Man will think that the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Worſhip there, was free from all defects, eſpecially conſidering that their Lyturgie was of humane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure, and yet our Saviour's preſence at this Worſhip, and joyning in it, did not make him guilty of the defects that cleaved to it. The Scribes and Phariſees taught unſound Doctrine as well as ſound; and yet our Saviour encouraged his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to hear them, only cautioning them to beware of the leaven of their Doctrine, leſt they ſhould receive it, or
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:106454:59"/>approve of it: Which had been a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, if their preſence in reference to the good, had been an approbation of the bad. Nor did the private Members of the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> by their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence at the diſorderly Adminiſtration of Holy things, complained of by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, in the 11. and 14. Chap. make themſelves guilty of that diſorder, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſomewhat elſe beſides their preſence. That's my firſt Reaſon.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The repetitions, abruptions, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſes, and the reading the Prayers out of a Book, are not oppoſite to, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of the matter and ends of Prayer: all that can be pretended, is, that they are leſs uſeful, leſs conducing to the ends of Worſhip. The things asked in that way are deſirable in themſelves; the ſuppoſed defect lies in the ſuppoſed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly way of asking them. For other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the petitioning for things in this way, tends to the ſame end as when the ſame things are prayed for in a ſuppoſed more orderly way, though comparatively with ſome diſadvantage. A greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of uſefulneſs doth not exclude a leſs, but only exceed it. A mode or <hi>medium</hi> of Prayer is not therefore uſeleſs becauſe another is more uſeful, eſpecially when a
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:106454:60"/>more uſeful one cannot be made uſe of and the other declined without a greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience otherwiſe. They will not ſay its unlawful to joyn in conceived Prayer with a Miniſter or private Chriſtian that is leſs able then another, and, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, far inferiour to ſome then preſent. A leſs uſeful verſion of the Pſalms doth not make it unlawful to ſing Pſalms by ſuch a verſion. The geſture of kneeling in Prayer is the beſt and meeteſt, and yet that doth not make the uſe of another geſture in Prayer unlawful. If the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer-Book, <hi>medium</hi> of Worſhip then be in the fore-mentioned reſpects, or any other, leſs uſeful then another, it might be indeed a reaſon inducing them that think ſo, to make uſe of another which they judge better, if they were at Liberty to do it without drawing on a greater inconvenience, ſuch as ſeparation is with all its ill effects. But otherwiſe can any Man think that the leſs uſefulneſs of a mode but of part of the publick Worſhip (for it is no more) to be a ſufficient ground of ſeparation, when there is a neceſſity of uſing the one, or practiſing the other. Under ſuch Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances doubtleſs a leſs uſeful mode of publick Worſhip is much more eligible then to run all the hazards, and to bring
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:106454:60"/>on all the evil effects of a ſeparation for the uſe of one but comparatively better. It is moſt certain that ſeparation upon account of a leſs uſeful mode tends more to the hurt and dammage of the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous intereſt in the main, then the uſe of a leſs uſeful mode of but part of the publick Worſhip can with any colour of reaſon or truth be pretended to do. All that can be pretended, is, that it tends leſs to the good of Religion, but not at all to its hurt, as ſeparation doth.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And laſtly, as to this: They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prove Communion in the Worſhip preſcribed by the Lyturgie to be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful upon account of its being impoſed by Man, and commanded by humane Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. Before they can prove this, they muſt prove ſuch Communion to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden of God (which, as I have been ſhewing before, cannot be done.) For that Law of God which will bear us out in doing a thing, cannot be repealed by the Law of Man commanding the ſame thing. There is no ſuch enmity or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtency between God's Laws and thoſe of Men which are but ſubordinate, or not oppoſite to God's, as that any thing ſhould become the leſs acceptable to God, meerly becauſe commanded by
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:106454:61"/>his Miniſter. Nay, we obey God in obeying the higher powers in ſuch things as are not contrary to his Laws; becauſe God hath commanded us to obey them in ſuch things. It is not a ſetting up of Man in God's ſtead till Man is obeyed againſt God, not when he is obeyed in ſubordination to him.</p>
                  <p>But let us turn the Tables a little, and ſuppoſe that the Law of the Land did forbid the uſe of any ſet Form of Prayer in the Church, (as ſometime the uſe of the Lyturgie was forbidden) and that all Miniſters were by Law commanded to pray extempory, would ſuch an impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or command make extemporary Prayer unlawful, and only a Form of Prayer then neceſſary? I ſuppoſe they will not ſay it would; and if not, then for the ſame reaſon why it would not make Prayer in that mode unlawful, it doth not make it unlawful in this.</p>
                  <p>Men uſe to plead their Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty againſt ſuch humane impoſitions. But the beſt uſe of Chriſtian Liberty, is ſtill to do thoſe things, which all things conſidered, tend moſt to common good, the edification of our ſelves and others, though otherwiſe and out of thoſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances we were under no obligation
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:106454:61"/>to do them. And thus did St. <hi>Paul</hi> make uſe of it, who beſt underſtood the uſe of his Chriſtian Liberty. <hi>Though I am free from all Men,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>yet have I made my ſelf a Servant unto all, that I might gain the more:</hi> To the Jews I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came as a Jew; to them that are without Law, as without Law, and all this <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the Goſpel ſake,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.19.23. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Goſpel in the main did go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern him (as it ſhould do us) in the uſe of his Chriſtian Liberty, ſometimes one way, and ſometimes another. And therefore we have him ſometimes againſt Circumciſion, that the truth of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel might be preſerved among the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.5. and 5.1. And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times making uſe of it for the furtherance of the Goſpel, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.3. And he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the Chriſtians to uſe their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to which they were called, not ſo much to pleaſe themſelves as <hi>to ſerve one another in Love;</hi> but by no means <hi>to uſe it as an occaſion to the fleſh,</hi> as ſome would have taught them, in caſting off the Rule and Government of Heathen Governours, Maſters, and Magiſtrates, under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of being Chriſt's Freemen, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.13. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1, 2, 3. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Jude</hi> 9. Now I have been ſhewing before, that
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:106454:62"/>a Liberty of a total diſ-uſe of the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie in the publick Worſhip as the caſe now ſtands, cannot be practicable with that advantage to the general intereſt of Religion, as the uſe of it may, as any Men of reaſon may eaſily diſcern, if they be not blinded with prejudice and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. An Argument may much rather be fetched from Chriſtian Liberty for the uſe of the Lyturgie under the preſent poſture of Circumſtances, then againſt it. For if God hath not limitted Prayer to one mode only, then Chriſtians are at Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to uſe any as occaſion ſhall require for the intereſt of Religion in the Main; and, conſequently, that which for the preſent the Law requires.</p>
                  <p>I have now near done with the ſecond Dividing-Principle: and when the whole I have ſaid about it hath been conſidered, I appeal to all who are able to make a judgment in the caſe, whether thoſe that ſeparate from our Proteſtant Pariſh-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, will ever be able to clear themſelves from the guilt of ſinful Schiſm, and cauſleſs ſeparation, and of all the miſchievous effects that have, and may proceed from it, or be occaſioned by it.</p>
                  <p>And to give yet the greater weight to
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:106454:62"/>the general ſcope of what I have ſaid about the Lawfulneſs of Communion in our Pariſh Congregations, and of the ſinfulneſs of ſeparating from them, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all pretences, I ſhall ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you the un-erring example of our Bleſſed Saviour in his holding local Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion when he was on Earth, with ſuch a Church as he did: which, for ought I can judge, was more corrupt both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Perſons and things, then any of our Pariſh-Churches are, though many of them, alas, are too bad indeed. 1. The High Prieſt-hood, the higheſt Office in the Church, in which Miniſtry, all the Worſhippers were concerned, was bought and ſold for Money, or otherwiſe undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obtained, and frequently tranſlated from one to another, contrary to God's appointment, of which we have an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count from <hi>Joſephus,</hi> beſides what we have in <hi>Luke</hi> 3.2. <hi>John</hi> 11.49.51. and 18.13. 2. Proviſions for the Temple-Service, were in part unduly obtained in the Corban way, <hi>Mar.</hi> 7.11. 3. The Holy Temple was profaned, being made a Houſe of Merchandize and a Den of Thieves, which was otherwiſe Holy by inſtitution as well as the matter of the Worſhip it ſelf. 4. The Law was
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:106454:63"/>corrupted by many falſe gloſſes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.5. The Commandments of Men were taught for Doctrines, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.9. 6. The Church cenſures were abuſed to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication of the beſt Men, <hi>John</hi> 9.22.34. 7. The Sadduces, who denyed the Reſurrection, or that there is Angel or Spirit, were not only tolerated, but were alſo a great and prevailing party in that Church. 8. The Scribes, Phariſees, Chief Prieſts, and Rulers, were perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and oppreſſive, proud, covetous, and hypocritical: and the common Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple generally ſo bad, as that they prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Barabbas</hi> before Jeſus, and had their hands in ſhedding the Blood of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: and they with the other were all of them together <hi>a Generation of Vipers, a ſinful and an adulterous Generation.</hi> In this lamentable condition was that Church then. Yet all this notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, our Saviour did not refrain the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip, but held Communion with this Church, both in Temple and Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue-Worſhip, as you may ſee in <hi>Luke</hi> 2.41, 42, 43. <hi>John</hi> 2.23. and 7.10. and 10.22, 23. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.17, 18. There is no Man ever had ſo good a mind as he, to ſoundneſs of Doctrine, purity of Worſhip and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:106454:63"/>and to right order and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline in the Church. And his Wiſdome was ſuch, as that he knew perfectly what was fitteſt to be done under ſuch Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of things, both in reference to his Father's Glory, the furtherance of Religion, the advancement of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Salvation of Men, for which he came into the World; and what courſe would beſt conduce to theſe ends, and what would not. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though as a publick Perſon he did not ſpare to reprove the corruptions of the time both in reſpect of Perſons and things, and to endeavour a Reformation in a regular way, yet he never attempted it by breaking off Communion with that Church in the publick Worſhip, and by erecting ſeparate Communities for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation ſake; which yet certainly he would have done, if that had been the better and nearer way to thoſe great ends but now mentioned.</p>
                  <p>And if Men had no other ends or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns then our Saviour had, me-thinks thoſe that are to learn of him, and not to teach him, ſhould not lay aſide thoſe means and methods which he made choice of to accompliſh his ends, or ever think to make a better choice then he had done.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:106454:64"/>If when thoſe who are ingenuous and truly conſciencious, have well conſidered theſe things, and yet after that ſhall continue ſeparatiſts from our Pariſh-Churchs I ſhall ſomewhat wonder how or which way they can ſatisfie themſelves in ſo doing. Me-thinks this unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and uncontroulable patern and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of our Saviour, of whom we are all to learn, and who hath left us an example that we ſhould tread in his ſteps, ſhould of it ſelf alone if there were nothing elſe to be ſaid in the caſe, put an end to all diſputes about this buſineſs, and ſatisfie the moſt ſcrupulous Chriſtian under Heaven.</p>
                  <p>The Jews initiating of Proſelytes by Baptiſm as well as by Circumciſion, was a humane addition to what God had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed: and yet for all that our Saviour made choice of Baptiſm by which to initiate Proſelytes into his Religion. He uſed a geſture in eating the Paſſeover, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from what was appointed at the firſt inſtitution, as <hi>Ainſworth</hi> obſerves on <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.6.11. Which things I might improve to ſeveral purpoſes: but becauſe they are not ſo directly appoſite to what I have laſt diſcourſed, I ſhall leave them to be pondered on by ſuch as are
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:106454:64"/>ſcrupulous over much, and who think no alteration of Circumſtances between the firſt and after-uſe of an inſtitution, will juſtifie a Circumſtantial variation from what was firſt practiſed thereabout.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="dividing_principle">
                  <head>III. <hi>Dividing Principle to be avoided.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Another Dividing Principle, is, That it doth not belong to the Higher Powers in a Nation profeſſing Chriſtianity, to intermeddle in any publick eſtabliſhment of that Religion, farther then to protect, countenance, and encourage the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of it in their Profeſſion. I call this a Dividing Principle, becauſe the Higher Powers doing more then ſo in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Divided the whole Nation into par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Pariſh-Churches, and having ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Goſpel-Ordinances to be Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in thoſe Congregations, and obliging, and conſtraining all profeſſing the true Chriſtian Religion in the Nation to attend the Worſhip of God in thoſe Aſſemblies; this being the National way as they call it, ſome do therefore ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from it. In oppoſition to this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding Principle, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That Nations profeſſing the true
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:106454:65"/>Chriſtian Religion, do upon that account according to the Scripture, ſtand related to God as his People in a large ſence, and in contradiſtinction to the Heathen and Infidel World.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That a National ſettlement of the Chriſtian Worſhip in the Pariſh-Churches by the Higher Powers, is more for the intereſt of Religion and Men's Salvation, then if there ſhould be none.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To begin with the firſt of theſe. When God by <hi>Abraham</hi> deſigned to ſet on foot a method of Reforming the World, he declared to him he would do it in a National way: <hi>As for me, my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is with thee, a Father of many Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhalt thou be: A Father of many Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have I made thee,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.4, 5. Meaning, I ſuppoſe, that that Reformation which was begun in him, by his Faith and Obedience in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the Idols of his Countrey upon God's call, and betaking himſelf to the Worſhip and Service of the true God, ſhould by degrees extend to the taking in of many Nations. God at the very firſt told him that <hi>he ſhould be a Bleſſing,</hi> and that in him, and in his Seed, all Nations ſhould be Bleſſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.2, 3. And by St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 4.16, 17. we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:106454:65"/>that God's promiſe of making <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> a Father of many Nations, was not in reſpect of many Nations deſcending from him in the way of Natural Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but by deriving from him that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith and holy Worſhip, which was tranſmitted down from him, not only to the Nation of the Jews, but alſo to the Nations of the Gentiles. To begin this Work in a National way, the Lord promiſed <hi>Abraham</hi> to give to his Seed, his Natural Seed, the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> as the place where this work ſhould be emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently begun in a National way. And all that Nation were accordingly brought into Covenant with God, and became his Church and People. And all the Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes of the Gentiles that forſook their Idols to joyn with them to Worſhip the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and were Circumciſed, were without any exception ſave that of legal uncleanneſs, to eat the Paſſeover, <hi>Numb.</hi> 9. And thus it held on in the way of gathering only ſome here and there out of the Nations of the Gentiles, untill Chriſt gave Commiſſion to Preach the Goſpel to all Nations, Baptizing them.</p>
                  <p>And as the time of bringing in whole Nations of the Gentiles in times of the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:106454:66"/>Goſpel drew nearer, ſo Predictions of it by the Prophets, were more particular and expreſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.15. <hi>He ſhall ſprinkle many Nations:</hi> to wit, as he promiſed in particular to the Jews to ſprinkle clean water upon them, to <hi>cleanſe</hi> them <hi>from all their filthineſs, and from all their Idols,</hi> Ezek. 36.25. And again, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.5. <hi>Behold, thou ſhalt call a Nation that thou kneweſt not, and Nations that knew not thee ſhall run unto thee.</hi> And God's call of a Nation, and a Nations Anſwer to that call, makes a Church, works a Relation between God and them; as ſome have well obſerved. And <hi>Zechariah,</hi> one of the laſt Prophets, ſpeaks yet more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, Chap. 2.11. <hi>And many Nations ſhall be joyned to the Lord in that day, and ſhall be his People.</hi> To be joyned to the Lord, and to be his People, plainly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie ſuch a Relation between God and them, as doth make them to be of his Church. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.43. <hi>The Kingdome of God ſhall be taken from you, and given to a Nation:</hi> that is, ſure Nationally, for otherwiſe we cannot ſay it was taken from all of that Nation of the Jews. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. <hi>The Kingdomes of this World are become the Kingdomes of the Lord, and of his Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:106454:66"/>
                  <p>Theſe Predictions have been fulfilled as Nations have Nationally imbraced and profeſſed the Chriſtian Religion. For it is a vain thing to think that theſe Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies have not yet at all been fulfilled now after the Goſpel hath been running its courſe theſe ſixteen hundred years to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh them. And if any have a mind to interpret theſe Propheſies of National Churches by that in <hi>Revel.</hi> 5.9. <hi>And haſt Redeemed us to God by thy Blood, out of every Kinred, and Tongue, and People and Nation:</hi> They may do well to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that the calling of a few out of Nations (according to their Notion) is not the calling of thoſe Nations them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Its one thing for Men to be brought to effectual Faith and ſincere Obedience by the Goſpel, and another to be brought to a general profeſſion of it. There are the many that are called, and yet but few that are the choſen, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.16. and 22.14. It is in the one ſenſe that they are ſaid to be Redeemed out of every Kinred, Tongue, People, and Nation; and in the other, that whole Nations are ſaid to be joyned to the Lord, and to be his People; for ſo they are by a general call and profeſſion. Every individual Perſon in a Nation that ſo profeſſeth and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:106454:67"/>Worſhippeth the true God in oppoſition to all falſe gods as to be called by his Name, are in Scripture denominated Sons and Daughters to God in a large ſenſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.6, 7. <hi>Bring my Sons from far, and my daughters from the ends of the Earth, even every one that is called by my Name.</hi> As the Worſhippers of Idols are called the Children of a ſtrange god, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.11. So in oppoſition to that, and in a large ſenſe, all that Worſhip the true God, are called his Children, as the Jews were, <hi>Diut.</hi> 14.1. When St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26. to all the Churches of <hi>Galatia, Ye are all the Children of God by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> it was ſure from their profeſſion of Faith in Chriſt Jeſus in their Baptiſm by which they put him on (as there he ſaith) that he ſo ſtiles them, and not from the effectualneſs of the Faith of every one of them: For he chargeth them with <hi>being removed from the Goſpel of Chriſt to another Goſpel,</hi> Chap. 1.6. with <hi>not obeying the Truth,</hi> Chap. 3.1. and tells them that <hi>he was afraid of them leſt he had beſtowed labour on them in vain,</hi> Chap. 4.11. that <hi>he ſtood in doubt of them,</hi> and was <hi>travelling in Birth again with them for the forming of Chriſt in them,</hi> ver. 19, 20. There are many that are the People
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:106454:67"/>of God by profeſſed Obligation on their part, that are not ſo by ſpecial intereſt in the promiſe on God's part, for want of performing the ſpecial Condition. And ſuch are the Servants of God, indeed; but they are called in Scripture <hi>Sloathfull Servants, unprofitable Servants, wicked Servants, fooliſh Virgins, Branches in Chriſt</hi> the Vine, that bear no Fruit.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A National ſettlement of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Worſhip in the Pariſh-Churches by the Higher Powers, is more for the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of Religion, and Men's Salvation, then if there ſhould be none. It is for the intereſt of Religion in a Nation that are of the true Religion by profeſſion, that the Higher Powers there being of the ſame Religion, do take order, 1. That God be publickly Worſhipped by the People in the uſe of Goſpel-Ordinances. 2. That places for publick Worſhip be provided for that end. 3. That Church-Officers competently qualified, be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to adminiſter thoſe Ordinances in thoſe places; and that maintenance be appointed them that they may attend that Work. 4. That all the People of the Chriſtian Profeſſion, be required to attend the publick Worſhip. 5. That this be enjoyned under ſuch moderate penalties,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:106454:68"/>as may ſecure the Law from contempt, or careleſs neglect. 6. That ſome be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to ſee the Law put in Execution: which yet cannot be practicable without a diſtribution of the whole into parts in the ſame, or ſome ſuch way as that is, by which the whole Nation is divided into Pariſhes. 7. That Church-Diſcipline be eſtabliſhed and duly exerciſed for the purging of the Church, and keeping it pure. The firſt of theſe particulars that the Higher Powers take care that God be publickly Worſhipped by the People, is evident of it ſelf. Nature teaches all Men to Worſhip him whom they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be their God, and by themſelves or others to teach thoſe under their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to do the like, as appears by univerſal practice. And the ſecond of the fore-mentioned particulars is conſequent upon the firſt, and the third upon the ſecond, and ſo on.</p>
                  <p>That theſe things are for the intereſt of Religion, every Man's reaſon will eaſily diſcern. For hereby a face of Religion will be kept up in every place in ſuch a Nation, and the means of Salvation will be ready at hand, and all will come under an obligation of Man's Law as well as God's, to make uſe of them. And hereby
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:106454:68"/>through the Bleſſing of God, knowledge and the fear of the Lord will be propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated more then if the People were all left at liberty to do that which is right in their own eyes, to provide, or not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide themſelves with ſuch helps, or to uſe or neglect them as they pleaſe. We ſee by experience that there is generally the leaſt face of Religion in thoſe places that have been moſt neglected in the publick proviſion. And it is upon the account of ſuch neceſſary things as theſe, that Kings and Queens were promiſed as a great Bleſſing to the Church under the Notion of <hi>Nurſing Fathers and Nurſing Mothers,</hi> to train up, and Educate their People in Religion, <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 49.23. And the better any Kings and Rulers are, the more careful, and the more zealous will they be to promote and propagate true Religion in their Dominions by their Authority. And uſually the ſucceſs anſwers the zeal and diligence of ſuch, as we ſee it did in the good Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> and their Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. When <hi>all Kings fall down before him, all Nations ſhall ſerve him,</hi> according to the Propheſie, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.11. It will be ſo with the People, when the Kings of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſubject themſelves to Chriſt, not only in their perſonal, but more eſpecially
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:106454:69"/>in their Regal capacity. For which cauſe it ſhould ſeem St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorted the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians, <hi>to make Supplications, Prayers, and Interceſſions, for Kings, and all that are in Authority;</hi> as for other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, ſo eſpecially for their Converſion to Chriſtianity (they being then Heathen) both that Chriſtians might live peaceable and quiet Lives in all godlineſs and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, and alſo that Chriſtianity might be propagated in their Dominions, to the Salvation of many the more: For this is implyed in the reaſon of the exhortation in theſe words: <hi>For this is good and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in the ſight of God our Saviour, who will have all Men to be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the Truth;</hi> 1 Tim. 2.2, 3, 4.</p>
                  <p>And when the primitive Chriſtians had accordingly for a long time travelled by fervent Prayer for the Converſion of the Heathen Emperours to Chriſtianity, at laſt they obtained their Petition in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> that famous Chriſtian Emperour: upon whoſe Victories over the Enemies to Chriſtianity, and the propagation of the Chriſtian Religion by publick Authority throughout his Dominions, that joyful acclamation was heard in the Church (as Interpreters underſtand) <hi>Now is come
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:106454:69"/>Salvation and ſtrength, and the Kingdome of our God, and the Power of his Chriſt,</hi> Revel. 12.10. Chriſtianity, and ſo the Kingdome of God, was in the Empire before by private mens profeſſion of it: but when it came to be backed by Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Edicts and Laws, and to be ſeconded by the power and ſtrength of the Empire; Then, and not till then, was that new Song ſung in the Church: <hi>Now</hi> is come Salvation and Strength, the Kingdome of our God, and the Power of his Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>I would it were better conſidered by ſome who would be thought great Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Popery, how that in this proper and eminent point of Popery, they ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolize with the Pope himſelf, and all that are thorow-Papiſts, <hi>viz.</hi> In denying Kings to have any power in matters Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical. When the ten Kings, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.13. parted with this Eccleſiaſtical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to the Pope upon his Uſurpation, they gave their Authority, which God had inveſted them with, as well as their Strength, unto the Beaſt. And as faſt as they fall off from him, they re-aſſume it again, as we ſee all Princes and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, of the Reformed Religion have done. And of all the Kings that have
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:106454:70"/>profeſſed Chriſtianity ever ſince there was a Nation profeſſing it, there hath not, I think, been one, but who have claimed a power about ordering Church-affairs, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſuch as have given their power and ſtrength unto the Beaſt. And ſhall we not then interpret and underſtand the Ancient Propheſies that went of them, by the event in what we ſee fulfilled?</p>
                  <p>That Kings may abuſe this power to the propagating a falſe Religion, or in corrupting the true, is no good Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the due uſe of it in propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the true. <hi>He is the Miniſter of God to thee for good,</hi> ſaith the Scripture: and as long as he doth that which tends to publick good, he is not out of his way to be ſure, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. Every Chriſtian is bound to promote the intereſt of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on according to his capacity: he that is head of a Family as ſuch is bound to do it: and ſo he that is head of a Kingdome, as ſuch is bound to do it likewiſe; every one is under an obligation to do it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Talents and ſeveral abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities.</p>
                  <p>It's true indeed, that ſince all ſuch as are the Higher Powers, <hi>are Miniſters of God for good</hi> to the People, and have no power from God to <hi>do any thing againſt the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:106454:70"/>Truth, but for the Truth;</hi> It is greatly to be wiſhed, and fervently to be prayed for in behalf of all Chriſtian Princes and Governours, that God would give them Wiſdome, that nothing may be impoſed upon their People by them in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, but what hath a plain and apt tendency one way or other to further Edification, or to help their Devotion: And that ſuch wayes and methods of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting theſe ends may be made uſe of, as are leaſt lyable to exception or diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thereby to cut off as much as may be, all occaſion of Diviſion and pretence of diſſatisfaction: that ſo Peace, Love, and Unity may be recovered, and the happy effects of them obtained.</p>
                  <p>Yet when all is done that can be done, there will in all National ſettlements of this Nature, be place for the Exerciſe of humane prudence. And indeed I know no Sect or party, but though they decry humane prudence about the Worſhip of God never ſo much, yet do make uſe of it themſelves in their Adminiſtration of Holy things, and are neceſſitated ſo to do if they will Worſhip God publickly at all. The Ordinances of Baptiſm, Lord's Supper, Word, and Prayer, as touching the matter and ſubſtance of them, are
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:106454:71"/>particularly and expreſly determined in Scripture: But many particulars about the Adminiſtration of theſe, are left to the guidance and direction of general Rules for Edification. It is not determined in particular what Prayers ſhall be made ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before or after the Adminiſtration of Baptiſm or the Lord's Supper, or what exhortation ſhall be made to the People upon the occaſion of them. It is not determined in particular how, or in what way or method the Word and Prayer ſhall be uſed in Church-Aſſemblies; As how much, and what part of the Scripture ſhall be read at one meeting, or how, or what way the Miniſter ſhall improve the Word by Preaching, as whether by what occurrs to his preſent thoughts upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of what is then read, or by utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what he hath prepared by painful ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies otherwiſe; or whether he ſhall do this with, or without the help of Notes. Nor is it particularly determined whether all, or part, or none of the publick Prayers ſhall be in a preſcribed Form, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Lord's Prayer, or whether any of it ſhall, or ſhall not be read out of a Book, or whether Prayer ſhall be made both before and after Sermon.</p>
                  <p>Now, in this caſe thoſe to whom it
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:106454:71"/>belongs to take order for the ſetling of God's publick Worſhip in a Nation, with the beſt advice they can take, will neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily be put upon conſidering whether it is beſt to leave all theſe things wholly to each Miniſter's Liberty and choyce, or wholly to limit them, or whether to leave them partly at Liberty, as in the Pulpit, and partly to limit them. And while they deliberate on theſe things, ſeveral circumſtances will come under conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; As the different abilities, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious tempers of the Miniſters, and the various capacities and tempers of the People; as whether that which may be beſt for ſome, may be beſt for all, or whether ſomewhat of a middle Nature may not beſt accommodate all: and what hath anciently been practiſed in the Church of God, and what is practiſed in other Reformed Churches; and which way is moſt likely to preſerve Truth and Peace in the Church, and the like. And when Men have only general Rules to guide and govern themſelves by in deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining ſuch things as theſe, it muſt be remembred that it is a thing incident to the holieſt and wiſeſt Men to differ in their application of particular caſes to general Rules, when a great variety of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:106454:72"/>Circumſtances are to be taken in to make a right judgment in the caſe: their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent meaſures of light, if not of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts too, expoſing them thereunto. Their late differences under a greater Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in this kind then can now be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is a ſufficient proof of this.</p>
                  <p>And when things of this Nature are done, &amp; determined upon the beſt terms, as is thought by them into whoſe hands the Providence of God hath caſt it, though it ſhould be otherwiſe, not only in the thoughts of many others, but alſo really in it ſelf; yet if nothing be thereby im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed as a Condition of Communion, but what Circumſtances conſidered, is Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, the reaſons formerly given may, I conceive, well ſway with all ſober and peaceable-minded Chriſtians, rather to make the beſt uſe they can of the preſent ſettlement, then to chuſe to ſeparate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not in all things to their mind. For if there ſhould not be a bearing with one another in ſuch leſſer differences for general Edification ſake, and the intereſt of Religion in the main, and for the maintenance of Peace and Love, till by diſcreet, ſober, and peaceable means thoſe that differ can work themſelves, or thoſe that differ from them, into a nearer
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:106454:72"/>agreement; how ſhould it ever be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that Chriſtians ſhould maintain ſuch fellowſhip upon their agreement in the ſubſtantials of Chriſtianity notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding circumſtantial differences, as for which the Scripture is far more expreſs, then it is for ſuch particular modes of Worſhip, as thoſe are about which they differ. If differences in judgment about Circumſtances whereby the ſubſtance of Religion is not in danger, ſhould be a ſufficient ground of ſeparation, its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable there would be almoſt as many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations as Churches in the World.</p>
                  <p>Having now done with what I had to ſay to take Men off from thoſe Dividing Principles which are chiefly conſiderable, I ſhall purſue my Directions for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to keep the Unity of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the bond of Peace, no further, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what plentiful proviſion there is already made for Direction in the <hi>Cure of Church-diviſions,</hi> as by others, ſo eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by that laborious Servant of the Lord, Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> I ſhall therefore conclude this Diſcourſe with a few mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to perſwade the ſeveral parties which are Divided, to Unite again, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace: And that all on all
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:106454:73"/>hands would manifeſt themſelves to be ſuch hearty lovers of Peace, Unity, and Charity, as for the ſake thereof thoſe that are uppermoſt, would count it no diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, but rather their glory, to conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to thoſe that are below: and that thoſe again, whoſe ſtanding is in the Valley, would not think it too much to travel up the Hill to meet them: And if it be thought too much to ſtrive who ſhall <hi>go before another in giving Honour,</hi> (Rom. 12.18.) yet if both ſorts that differ, would but go as far as they well may, both in reſpect of Conſcience and prudence, towards compounding the difference; how ſoon, and how eaſily might both ends be brought together, and the bond of Peace which hath been bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, be pieced again. To this end con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, and lay to heart thoſe few things which I ſhall lay before you.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. I ſhall commend to you the beſt patern which you can imitate, and againſt which there can be no exception, and that is God himſelf: who though he be ſo infinitely above all, as to ſtand in no need of the Friendſhip of Men, yet out of the Infinite goodneſs of his Nature, <hi>hath humbled himſelf,</hi> not only <hi>to behold the things on Earth,</hi> but even to ſeek the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:106454:73"/>reconciliation of his Enemies to himſelf, and to propoſe new and eaſie terms of Friendſhip, when the old had been viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>God was in Chriſt reconciling the World unto himſelf, not imputing their treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes unto them,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.19. And not to reconcile them to himſelf only, but alſo to one another in their common head and center of Union, Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>That in the diſpenſation of the fulneſs of time he might gather together in [one] all things in Chriſt, both which are in Heaven and which are on Earth,</hi> Epheſ. 1 10. And to that end hath ſent forth Ambaſſadours of Peace to beſeech them to be reconciled to God, and to bring them all to the <hi>Unity of the Faith, and knowledge of the Son of God,</hi> Epheſ. 4.13. And how can we think our ſelves to be partakers of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature, unleſs we find ſome reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of this goodneſs of God's Nature in our ſelves, inclining and diſpoſing us to concord and good agreement with fellow-Chriſtians, by removing out of the way all that unneceſſarily hinders it. <hi>Bleſſed are the Peace-makers, for they ſhall be called the Children of God,</hi> Mat. 5.9. And why the Children of God? but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe herein they reſemble him who is the God of Peace, that loves Peace, and
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:106454:74"/>ſeeks Peace, and delights to ſee Men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning it, and labouring at it, with heart, head, tongue, and hand. <hi>Be ye therefore</hi> one and all, <hi>followers of God as dear Children, and walk in Love,</hi> Eph. 5.1, 2. <hi>Be perfect, be of one mind, live in Peace, and the God of Love and Peace ſhall be with you,</hi> 2 Cor. 13.11. Can you be ambitious of any greater Honour then to be like God? A likeneſs to God is the higheſt Honour and perfection the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of any Creature is capable of: And to live in Love and Peace, and to ſeek Peace, and to be Peace-makers, is the way to be like him. <hi>If we love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, God dwelleth in us, and his love is perfected in us,</hi> 1 John 4.12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If you count it either matter of Honour or comfort to be of a temper like Chriſt, or if you think it will give you any confidence towards him for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and at his coming (as undoubtedly it will) then by this be perſwaded like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to endeavour with all your might that the Unity of the Spirit may be kept in the bond of Peace. For the heart and Soul of Chriſt is exceedingly ſet upon Union and good agreement of all that believe in him: though they cannot all know alike and think alike in every thing,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:106454:74"/>yet for all that he is greatly deſirous they ſhould all hold together as one in Faith and Love. And therefore in that ſolemn Prayer of his to his Father, <hi>John</hi> 17. when he was leaving the World, he ſingles out this in ſpecial as the matter of his requeſt to his Father in one of the laſt Prayers he was to make in this World, <hi>that they all might be one, and be perfected in one.</hi> His heart and deſire was ſo full of this, and ſo ſet upon it, that he is at it over and over, mentioning it no leſs then four times in the ſame Prayer, <hi>ver.</hi> 11.21, 22, 23. And why was his heart ſo much in this? Was it, think you, for himſelf, or for us? For his own ſake, or for ours? He deſired no greater thing for himſelf then to be <hi>Glorified with the Glory he had with the Father before the World was,</hi> before ever he entred upon his Mediatory Office, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. No, it was for us, Men, and for our comfort and benefit that he ſo much deſired it, as knowing how much the Peace, comfort, and Edification of his People depended upon it; and how much the Converſion of the World depended on it, as neceſſary to make a right repreſentation of Chriſt to the World, that they might believe that the Father had ſent him.</p>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:106454:75"/>
                  <p>And was his heart ſo much in it! And did he concern himſelf ſo much about it for our ſakes! And ſhall we our ſelves value it ſo little as to prefer little and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable things before it, and that rather for will and humour then any tye of Conſcience! O, God forbid. If we do, it is a ſign we do not yet well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the things that belong to our peace, but that they are hid from our eyes.</p>
                  <p>And if Chriſt's heart was ſo much ſet upon the Unity and Concordance of his followers, we muſt needs think they are Men according to his own heart that heartily deſign, deſire, and endeavour it too. And is not that honour enough? Which ſounds of moſt Honour to <hi>David?</hi> That he was a King? Or, that he <hi>was a Man after God's own heart?</hi> And who are like to be moſt dear unto Chriſt, but thoſe who are moſt like him, and make one heart with him?</p>
                  <p>The more you ſhall find your hearts run out to this thing, as Chriſt's did; the more you find your ſelves of his mind, ſpirit, and temper herein, the better aſſurance you will have (and the greater comfort in that aſſurance) of your dwelling in him, and he in you: <hi>Hereby we know that we dwell in him, and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:106454:75"/>he in us, becauſe he hath given us of his Spirit,</hi> 1 John 4.13. <hi>But if any Man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his,</hi> Rom. 8.9.</p>
                  <p>Truly if Men were but as forward to gratifie and pleaſe our Lord in this that is ſo pleaſing to him, as they ſeem to be in ſome other things in which he never diſcovered himſelf to take any ſuch plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, things would be quite at another paſs among us. And yet if pleaſing him be the buſineſs, and not ſomewhat elſe, why ſhould not we be moſt for that in which he moſt delights?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Your contentions and Diviſions if you will ſtill live in them, and maintain them, will hinder your Spiritual improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and keep you from thriving by the means of grace which you enjoy. It was a ſad thing that St. <hi>Paul</hi> charged upon the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> viz. That <hi>their coming together, and exerciſing</hi> themſelves in the Holy Ordinances of the Lord, <hi>was not for the better, but for the worſe,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.17. <hi>Now in this that I declare unto you, I praiſe you not, that you come not to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for the better, but for the worſe.</hi> But what was the cauſe of this, or upon what doth he ground this charge of their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backward in Religion? Verily it was
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:106454:76"/>their Diviſions that was the cauſe of this miſchief. <hi>For firſt of all,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>when you come together in the Church, I hear that there are diviſions among you,</hi> ver. 18. That Church abounded in Spiritual gifts, <hi>being enriched in every thing, in all utterance and all knowledge, ſo that they came behind in no gift,</hi> Chap. 1.5.7. They thrived in theſe indeed: but then they went back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in their Humility and Charity, and goodneſs of their Spirit and temper, which made the Apoſtle to ſpend almoſt a whole Chapter in commending Charity above Spiritual gifts to them, beſides the ſeveral hints he gives of their being <hi>puffed up.</hi> Though they might well have been Spiritual Chriſtians, conſidering the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity and means they had to make them ſuch: yet becauſe of <hi>Euvring, Strife,</hi> and <hi>Diviſions</hi> among them, ſome follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one Teacher, and ſome another in oppoſition; St. <hi>Paul</hi> could not (as he ſaith) <hi>write to them as to Spiritual, but only as to Carnal,</hi> ſuch as were but <hi>Babes</hi> ſtill, and unthriven in the Life and Spirit of Chriſtianity; their envying, ſtrife, and diviſions, keeping them thus low un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the means of higher attainments in grace, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3.</p>
                  <p>The truth is, Diviſions, Wranglings,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:106454:76"/>and Janglings, and Contentions, eat out the very heart of Religion. Men may grow rich in a Form of knowledge, and expreſs a great zeal for the out ſide of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and yet in the mean time be lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing in the very vitals of Chriſtianity, when that knowledge and zeal is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and ſpent for the farthering of Peace and Love, with other Chriſtian Virtues. Your Diviſions and Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Chriſtians, will be as a Worm at the root of your Tree, that will keep it from thriving, whatever coſt you other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe beſtow upon it.</p>
                  <p>If then you have any mind to keep up Religion in heart among us, and not to have your Wine to become as Water, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving loſt its Spirit: If you would have the Goſpel-Ordinances yield their increaſe, and your Religion not degenerate into Form: If you would yield the Lord the acceptable and pleaſant Fruit of all his coſt, and not ſuch as is ſtarvie, harſh, and unſavoury: If you would not <hi>turn the Fruit of Righteouſneſs into Hemlock:</hi> If you would be free from ſuch a diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per as will hinder your Spiritual reliſh, and convert your food to a noxious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and ſubject you to a ſpiritual lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing in the midſt of a plentiful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:106454:77"/>for Spiritual health and growth; Then lay aſide your diviſions about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of doubtful diſputation, and follow after the things which make for peace, and things whereby you may edifie one another in love.</p>
                  <p>What knowledge ſoever you have, and what zeal ſoever you expreſs for any truth as you conceive it to be, yet if while you hold faſt other things, you let go Charity, your knowledge of, and your zeal in proſecuting and promoting the ſame, though it were to the loſing of your life, will profit you nothing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.2.3. <hi>I hough I underſtand all myſteries and all knowledge, and though I give my Body to be burned, and have not Charity, it profiteth me nothing.</hi> A thing which neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerns all ſuch to mind, that are more careful and tender leſt ſome other controverted and ſuppoſed truth ſhould ſuffer, then charity, peace, and concord ſhould ſuffer; and care not what rents and diviſions they make, ſo they may but propagate their particular opinion. If there be bitter zeal (as ſome tranſlate it) glory not of thy knowledge, and lie not againſt the truth, in ſaying that's the way to promote it, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.14. If you would thrive under the means of grace
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:106454:77"/>indeed, and be growing up to perfection, then be ſure to be much for Charity and Unity. You have much talk of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection among ſome, and many that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to it that are far from it, but I think it conſiſts in nothing more next our love to God, then in the Saints Love and Unity. This is the cry of the Scripture: <hi>That they made [perfect in one]</hi> John 17.23. <hi>Be perfect, be of one mind, live in Peace,</hi> 2 Cor. 13.11. <hi>Above all theſe put on Charity, which is the bond of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectneſs,</hi> Col. 3.14. <hi>If we love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, God dwelleth in us, and his love is [perfected] in us,</hi> 1 John 4.12.</p>
                  <p>If ſome do grow in grace after they have fallen into dividing wayes, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating practiſes (as I am not ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable, but to think that they do, while the errour lyes not in their will, but in their judgment) yet this growth is not to be attributed at all to that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they differ from other good Chriſtians, not of their way, who grow in grace too, but to thoſe ſound Principles of Chriſtianity wherein both the one and the other are agreed. And I have good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to think that the ſame improvement of thoſe unqueſtionable Principles by which they grow in grace, their ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:106454:78"/>notwithſtanding, would ſet them much forwarder in that growth, in caſe they were at Liberty from the intangle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſeparation, then under them it can: Becauſe thoſe wayes of Diviſion and Separation, do Naturally tend to narrow Men's Spirits and Charity, and to cauſe them to think that many are not of the Church of Chriſt, which indeed are: and to have low thoughts of many, that yet are highly eminent in the Church for their worth and Service; and all becauſe they are not of their way: and beſides, through prejudice they deprive themſelves of many happy advantages of Spiritual growth, which otherwiſe they would make uſe of. And thoſe that abound moſt in a well-grounded and regular Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, have, doubtleſs, the more of God's preſence and aſſiſtance with them for their Spiritual growth and comfort too, as others for want of it, have the leſs. <hi>If he that dwelleth in Love dwelleth in God, and God in him</hi> (1 Joh. 4.16.) then thoſe that abound moſt in Love, muſt needs have moſt of God's preſence, both to aſſiſt, quicken, and comfort them. <hi>Live in Peace, and the God of Love and Peace ſhall be with you,</hi> to increaſe theſe and to help you to propagate them
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:106454:78"/>(2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11.) and to give you great Peace in ſo doing, as ſome have found by Experience.</p>
                  <p>But though the wayes of ſeparation among us, do but as the Rickets, hinder ſome in their growth, and not totally deprive them of it, yet it is to be feared they make ſome others much worſe then they were before they came into them: more goodly and ſelf-conceited, more proud and imperious, ſlighting and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing others that are much better then themſelves, and over-valuing themſelves quite upon account of the Form and Church they are got into: and more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable in cenſuring others as carnal, as time-ſervers, as Men of the World, only becauſe of the National way, and not of theirs, though otherwiſe never ſo worthy. Many of theſe are growing indeed, but it is farther and farther into ſeparation, till at laſt they commence <hi>Quakers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. If you prize your comfort, prize harmony and good agreement, not among this or that ſort or party only, but among all that do agree in things of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity to Salvation to all. For thoſe that are living, and not dead, or benumb'd Members of Chriſt's Body,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:106454:79"/>cannot but be pained with the rending of one Member of that Body from another. <hi>If one Member ſuffer, all the Members ſuffer with it,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.26. Was it not a ſad ſight to ſee the Man, in <hi>Mar.</hi> 5.5. cutting himſelf with ſtones? And an Argument that he was poſſeſſed with an evil Spirit? And I pray you how much leſs doleful is it to ſee the People of God, Members of the ſame Body, cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and wounding themſelves? For ſo they do when they cut and wound one another: <hi>For they are Members one of another,</hi> Rom. 12.5. Alas, how unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural is this! <hi>For no Man yet ever hated his own fleſh.</hi> Certainly where thus it is, they are under a Spiritual phrenzy and madneſs, and are objects of very great commiſſeration as well as occaſions of great trouble and diſturbance in the Church of God. But, O, the <hi>Comfort of Love</hi> (as the Apoſtle phraſeth it, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1.) and the pleaſantneſs of Peace, and the delight of harmony, which is like a well-tuned Inſtrument where there is no jarring. <hi>Behold how good and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant a thing it is for Brethren to dwell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Unity!</hi> Pſal. 133.1. A great part of the comfort of a Chriſtian in this World, lyes in his Communion with
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:106454:79"/>Saints: <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>the Saints and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent were all his delight.</hi> Pſal. 16.3. And therefore a breach in this, muſt needs make a breach in a Chriſtians comfort.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The Chriſtian cauſe and intereſt in in the World calls loudly upon all ſuch as would approve themſelves to have any Love for it, or to be any Friends to it, and not betrayers of it, to Unite, and to cloſe up the Diviſions that are among us, and not to perſiſt in ſeparating practiſes, or to do any thing that contributes thereto, but the contrary. One great means of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitating the belief of the Goſpel, and of propagating the Chriſtian Religion, and of bringing it into reputation in the World, is the Union and good agreement of all Chriſt's followers. And therefore he prayed ſo earneſtly, as we heard before, <hi>that they all might be one, as he and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are one, that they alſo might be perfect in one,</hi> and all for this end, <hi>that the World might believe that the Father had ſent him,</hi> Joh. 17.20, 21. That Men might believe that he came from God indeed, and that he was no Impoſtor, but that his Goſpel is the infallible Truth, and that Religion which is taught thereby, is the only true Religion. For Chriſt's followers are thoſe by whom the Goſpel is upheld in
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:106454:80"/>the World, and held forth and witneſſed to the World: <hi>They hold forth the Word of Life</hi> (Phil. 2.16.) <hi>they are the Pillar and ground of the Truth,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.15. And the more unanimous theſe are in judgment, affection, and teſtimony, the ſtronger and more authentick will their teſtimony be, &amp; the more Men will be drawn to conſider it, and to lay to heart the import of it. But the more they are divided about it, the more this Goſpel, this Religion, comes under ſuſpition in the minds of many: and from their differing about leſſer things, the ignorant, the weak, and unbelieving, will draw arguments of ſuſpition and heſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about the greater, and be ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the uncertainty of the whole, by their differing about a part; eſpecially when their difference riſes ſo high, and becomes ſo notorious and publick, as it does when they ſeparate about it. This is lamentably experienced, not only in the continued infidelity of Jews and Turks, but alſo in that Atheiſm and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſciſm, which hath ſo exceedingly increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon us ſince theſe ſad times of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion and Separation among us. Our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions unſettle the minds, unhinge and diſtract the Souls of many, that they know not whom to follow, or where to fix: and
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:106454:80"/>by this means they are expoſed to be practiſed upon by ſeducers, and carried away. Your Diviſions encourageth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers, and the Adverſaries of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion in their deſigns againſt you, and invites them to attempt upon you; So that as long as you keep up your Diviſions, they will make an advantage of it, grow upon you, and get ground, and by little and little draw away your ſtrength; and in concluſion, over-maſter you, if by Uniting, you prevent them not. Your Adverſaries know the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>divide them in</hi> Jacob, <hi>and ſcatter them in</hi> Iſrael, if you do not; and of thoſe words, <hi>A Kingdome divided againſt it ſelf, cannot ſtand.</hi> It hath been, no doubt, their practice by all the artifice they could, to raiſe and foment your Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, as it is ſtill to continue and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe them, as deſigning ruine to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant intereſt thereby. And will you gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie them herein? And become their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to accompliſh your own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and the deſtruction of that cauſe and intereſt which ſhould be more dear to you then your Lives? God forbid. And therefore let no leſſer intereſts of worldly advantage, be it profit, be it honour among Men, or reputation among a party, tempt
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:106454:81"/>you to betray this greater intereſt of your Lord and Maſter, of Religion, and of your Souls. Be not herein penny wiſe, and pound fooliſh. Revive not that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.21. <hi>All ſeek their own, not the things of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Expoſe not Religion to loſs and dammage in the main, and in the ſubſtance of it, by being too tenacious of mutable Circumſtances. Be not ſo concerned for your Cabbin, as to expoſe the Ship to ſinking through your neglect.</p>
                  <p>I have now done: Only remember, I pray you, that the things wherein the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided parties profeſſedly agree, are ſuch as carry in them the main of Chriſtianity, and will make good Chriſtians indeed, if lived up to. Whereas the things upon which we divide, are but diſputable opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, the beſt of which on the one ſide or the other, will never make a good Chriſtian without the other. And you know what account God made of Men's zeal though it were for his own inſtitutions, as among the Jews of old, when they were greatly guilty of ſins againſt Charity. Though Men be never ſo Orthodox in, and zealous for their opinions, yet if they have not Charity, they are but as ſounding braſs, or a tinkling Cymbal. A wiſe Man will
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:106454:81"/>not therefore value himſelf by that which is proper to ſuch or ſuch a party, but by that Charity, Humility, and Sobriety of mind with other graces, which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to thoſe that are good indeed, in each party: and by theſe he will value any man of what party ſoever, and how different ſoever from himſelf in by-opinions. If thoſe of each party then would but ſteer by this compaſs, and proportion their zeal to the Nature of things, labouring more to leſſen differences, to make peace, and to recover Charity, then to propagate thoſe things which as they are more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, ſo at beſt are leſs acceptable to God, and leſs profitable unto Men; and, conſequently, leſs atractive of their zeal; I ſhould not doubt but that in a little time, things would be at a much better paſs in the Church of God, then for the preſent we ſee them to be.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:106454:82"/>
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>THere is great reaſon to think that many of the Non-Conformiſts do hold it Lawful for Perſons in the capacity of private Members to joyn in parochial Communion, who yet do not do ſo themſelves. The five diſſenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that lived in ſeparation from paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Communion, yet did in their Apola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getical Narration profeſs before God and the World, <hi>that all that conſcience of defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they conceived cleaved to our Pariſh-Churches, or of the unwarrantable power of Church-Governours exerciſed therein, did never work in them any other thought, much leſs opinion, but that multitudes of the Pariſh-Congregations, were the true Churches and Body of Chriſt, and the Miniſtry thereof a true Miniſtry.</hi> And I have no reaſon to doubt but that very many of the preſent Non-Conformiſts that never went ſo far as thoſe, are of the ſame opinion, who yet live not in communion with thoſe Pariſh-Churches, though they live among them. And I cannot but wonder that the ſence they muſt needs have of the ill tendency of our Diviſions, and of the deſirableneſs of Peace and Unity, ſhould not deter them from making, or keeping the breach wider then needs, wide then the neceſſity of not
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:106454:82"/>ſinning, puts them upon. For it cannot be denied, but that it is a duty incombent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chrſtians, and becoming all that love &amp; long for peace &amp; unity in the Church, to go as far as ever a good Conſcience will carry them towards the leſſening of our diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and cloſing up the breach among us.</p>
               <p>They cannot but know as well as all other men, that to break Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and rend the Church, where men are not neceſſitated to do ſo or to ſin, is Schiſm. And I muſt needs ſay they put the Charity of their Friends hard to it, not to think they condemn by their practice, what they allow in their judgment, while by ſeparation they break the Unity of the Church, which according to their own judgment, they might forbear to do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin.</p>
               <p>If they think their conceſſion touching the Lawfulneſs of Lay-Communion with our Pariſh-Churches will free them from the guilt of Schiſm, though they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves keep in no ſuch Communion, I may well pray them to conſider, whether that very thing doth not render their Schiſm in ſome reſpect more criminal then theirs who ſeparate as accounting our Churches no true Churches; ſince it ſeems to proceed more from errour in the will (which is
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:106454:83"/>errour of the worſt kind) than Schiſm in the others doth; and ſince their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; practice ſeem more to enterfeire, and to render them ſelf-condemned in their way. When <hi>Peter</hi> knew that the difference between the believing Jews and the believing Gentiles was no ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ground of ſeparation between them, and yet did withdraw and ſeparate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from the believing Gentiles, for fear of diſpleaſing the believing Jews; St. <hi>Paul withſtood him to his face, becauſe he was worthy to be blamed,</hi> and ſo much the rather, becauſe he drew <hi>Barnabas</hi> and other Chriſtians into <hi>the ſame diſſimulation</hi> with himſelf, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11, 12, 13.</p>
               <p>Theſe things conſidered; One would think they ſhould apprehend it far more ſafe, and leſs ſcandalous, and more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceable to Peace, Unity, and Love, and a more regular way of obtaining the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of burthens, for thoſe Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Miniſters as can, to maintain Communion as private Members with the Pariſhes, and to perſwade their hearers to do ſo too; though otherwiſe they ſhould think it fit for the exrciſe of their gifts and function, at convenient times to improve His Majeſties Indulgence to Preach in other places beſides the Temples.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106454:83" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
